<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<title>Chris L's blog about things</title>
<id>https://lcmchris.github.io/</id>
<link rel="alternate" href="https://lcmchris.github.io/"/>
<link rel="self" href="https://lcmchris.github.io/rss.xml"/>
<updated>2024-12-07T21:55:12.720Z</updated>
<author>
<name>Chris L</name>
</author>
<entry>
<title>Alpha catan: AI from the ground up</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/alpha_catan"/>
<id>https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/alpha_catan</id>
<published>2024-10-23T00:00:00.000Z</published>
<updated>2024-10-23T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
<content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1 data-svelte-h="svelte-1sga3">Building an AI</h1> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-1bsdffq">For the better part of the last year, I’ve been working on a little project I called <a href="https://github.com/lcmchris/alpha-catan" rel="nofollow"><code>alpha-catan</code></a>. I wanted to work on something just fun and interesting. Nothing related to business or anything that is even (remotely) useful. Just pure unadulterated fun. The project I ended up working on is trying to build and AI that plays Catan.</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-9pqyyz">Now, Settlers of Catan is a pretty famous board game which I have personally despised for ages. Apart from the terrible experiences of fights during Catan, I strongly believe there are 2 fundamental flaws of the game.</p> <ol data-svelte-h="svelte-8jfke"><li><p>Economy acceleration through luck: There is a strong economy acceleration effect. Good rolls give you resources which gives you more settlements… giving you more chances for good rolls. The <code>skill</code> is where to put your settlements. This however creates a situation where in some games you become merely an observer waiting for the winner to slowly play out the game.</p></li> <li><p>Trading: Many will argue the main game is the trading. From my experience, it is merely a tool to abuse new players. There is no reason really to trade as it is a zero-sum game. You would only accept a trade if you would increase your win% and a trade cannot do it for both parties of the trade. The only argument is if coming 2nd vs 3rd matters (which in general party games, it doesn’t).</p></li></ol> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-40e95f">These flaws are also why I believe a relatively simple model can beat the majority of players. If the only action that matters is mostly the first one, then it should be relatively simple to solve!
Armed with the <code>Hands on Machine learning book</code> and my hatred of Catan, I started working on building the model and the controller that goes with it.</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-13xu26x">Objective: Beat average player on colonist.io</p> <h2 data-svelte-h="svelte-1fb4wts">Building the model</h2> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-fvt5e1">On the outset, I wanted to do most things from scratch meaning I decided to not use a framework or any existing repos. I wanted to learn the basics of ML/RL and I got a lot of inspiration from the <a href="https://www.kaggle.com/code/scaomath/simple-neural-network-for-mnist-numpy-from-scratch" rel="nofollow">toy mnist problem with numpy</a> and <a href="https://karpathy.github.io/2016/05/31/rl/" rel="nofollow">Karpathy’s pong writeup</a>.</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-83iqor">The model I wanted to build is a basic one. For input game state, predict a suitable action.</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-f4xss3">Inputs</p> <ul data-svelte-h="svelte-12ac24k"><li>Game state<ul><li>Players resources</li> <li>Players dev cards</li> <li>Board state</li></ul></li></ul> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-1nopgm9">Prediction:</p> <ul data-svelte-h="svelte-eu4zyn"><li>Action to perform</li></ul> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-a94typ">To model multiple actions per turn, we predict until the model sets pass. This assumes that each action is the same regardless of if it is part of a chain of actions or not.</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-8vxacn">Example: Turn</p> <ul data-svelte-h="svelte-qoa2av"><li>Action 1</li> <li>Action 2</li> <li>Action 3</li> <li>until… Pass</li></ul> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-1rmwk5o">To start off with and not wanting to scale up training a lot, I focused on a 2-player rendition of the game. It is simpler letting me focus on training to win.</p> <h2 data-svelte-h="svelte-152aplx">Metrics</h2> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-nlgiw7">The main metric I looked at is <strong>turns to win</strong>. This helps ensure that they get generically better and better. The other are standard ML metrics <strong>avg loss</strong> (indicating how close action vs prediction) and <strong>avg rewards</strong> (the number of rewards for each player).
The expectation is that <strong>turns to win</strong> trends low, <strong>avg loss</strong> trends low and <strong>avg rewards</strong> tampers to a steady level.</p> <h3 data-svelte-h="svelte-4dgk93">Reward allocation and the law of large numbers</h3> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-e2bwqz"><strong>Reward allocation</strong> is a tricky business and I struggled in finding a good one. It’s essentially coming up with an intuition and then trying to build for it. For instance, the earliest edition involved only rewarding winners. This is basically running experiments!
The main difficulty comes from which action to reward. In this simple example below:</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-emdpmv">A → B → C → D → E → Win</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-i8iq3f">… it’s unclear how much reward to allocate to each of the actions. The best reward is to reward for winning and let the model learn which actions are important. However, the longer the list of actions, the more fuzzy the allocation gets. In theory, based on the law of large numbers, it doesn’t matter (too much) but not having intermediate rewards drastically lower training speed. However, on the flip-side, overengineering the rewards would put too much human intuition to it and make it work via defined rules rather than learned rules.</p> <h4 data-svelte-h="svelte-jlonrx">Rewarding winners</h4> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-1swfj91">The thought was the as you reward the winner’s actions, it will keep competing until it becomes the best.
Here shows the metrics:</p> <h4 data-svelte-h="svelte-1ou8k3e">Rewarding winners, Penalizing losers</h4> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-1kjijqm">Other than that, we could also penalize losers. This will speed up</p> <h4 data-svelte-h="svelte-1e74uz1">Rewarding Settlements and Cities</h4> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-1ncrynk">Settlements and cities are pretty useful. Let’s reward them</p> <h4 data-svelte-h="svelte-p6q0xq">Rewarding points</h4> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-1ezer4u">A limitation of the settlements and cities approach is that it does not reward you if you get dev cards and or longest roads etc.</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-fn9lcc">Rewarding points could be a good middle ground.</p> <h4 data-svelte-h="svelte-1niq3xs">Training by evolution</h4> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-miszf9">An alternative to training on each player winning and losing is to train on the average winner over a batch. Although this could be slower (1/2 of rewards), it should be more accurate on which side is better, giving a better gradient.</p> <h4 data-svelte-h="svelte-b6sbqq">Action space rebalancing</h4> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-1t3ou9h">One thing that I noticed while training is that it overprioritised non-passing. A simple look at the action space and it’s became clear that because most actions have more than one action, passing is rarely randomly chosen. Rebalancing by a factor of the available actions looks to be a good idea. The idea here is to make passing initially the most possible action and let it slowly fall down.</p> <h2 data-svelte-h="svelte-j321vg">Building the colonist.io controller</h2> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-1oizk1m">The colonist.io controller was much more difficult and time consuming than I thought. Because of a lack of apis to get the state of the game. The difficulty increases because colonist.io uses a html canvas to display the game. This means it’s not possible to search for elements. What I ended up having to building an image matcher in order to get the state of the game. This includes mapping each of the little settlements and city icons and use cv2 to find where it matches the most. Here is the list of all little images.</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-8q3uq8">[]</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-k52p0j">There are essenetially many timeouts added to wait out animations. The images do not always match 100% making it also a bit unreliable.</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-1w687bo">The canvas itself is also not the only piece of the information puzzle. The messages also need to be parsed inorder to provide additional information on whether dev cards are, what was rolled and what resources was gained.</p> <h3 data-svelte-h="svelte-zflkhf">Combining the two</h3> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-g6jzlq">Using the state gathered by the controller, I pass it to our latest and greatest model to battle it out with the colonist.io AI.</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-5r8q5f">Here’s a short video of this.</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-tj1f3y">Over 100 games… we won…</p>]]></content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Breaking down the frontend ecosystem</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/frontend_breakdown"/>
<id>https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/frontend_breakdown</id>
<published>2024-12-07T00:00:00.000Z</published>
<updated>2024-12-07T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
<content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1 data-svelte-h="svelte-1uuvvd5">Reading up on how frontend really works</h1> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-j36ixk">There’s so many frameworks, paradigms these days that keeping track of how frontend works is quite tricky.
It’s very easy to get started on this frameworks. Boilerplates makes this especially easy. Running:
<code>npm create vite@latest my-vue-app -- --template react</code> creates an application in a flash! This makes getting started on a website or web application extremely easy. What this doesn’t do is teach you how things work under the hood. The ease of usage has made all the tech underneath seem like magic. It’s good in a sense that it makes you work quicker (which is the main purpose of all tools) but bad in the sense that it abstracts all the details out. This makes choosing tools and paradigms you use much less obvious.</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-13wz6tk">As someone who did not go through computer science this knowledge was never with me but I’m determined to get to the bottom of it.</p> <h2 data-svelte-h="svelte-1d39hz">What does a website mean?</h2> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-55dd7j">What is a browser? A browser is application that renders a websites. At its core, it works by fetching from a webserver via HTTP request, a html file. It then uses this to paint a page. This is what happens when you access an URL. A URL points to a particular server via DNS. Remember when you originally purchase a domain from GoDaddy? GoDaddy gives you access to a domain and ability to change the DNS records. Using this and modifying the A record, you can redirect a url to a webserver ip.</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-10ynw1i">Simplified</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-1yhoq0">URL -&gt; DNS -&gt; Webserver ip</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-gzd4y6">Key point. All you need is to send html files to client browsers. JS and Css are additional sauce.</p> <h2 data-svelte-h="svelte-10zjy34">Routing</h2> <h2 data-svelte-h="svelte-1nepxpi">How does bundling work? Transpliers, Minifiers and Uglifiers</h2> <h4 data-svelte-h="svelte-1jjh8e6">ES modules!</h4> <h2 data-svelte-h="svelte-am6st7">Frontend Infrastructure</h2> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-1tucaym"><a href="https://vercel.com/docs/projects/domains" rel="nofollow">https://vercel.com/docs/projects/domains</a> <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Root_name_server" rel="nofollow">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Root_name_server</a></p>]]></content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Is physical writing still important in our generation?</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/is_writing_important"/>
<id>https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/is_writing_important</id>
<published>2024-01-01T00:00:00.000Z</published>
<updated>2024-01-01T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
<content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1 data-svelte-h="svelte-1ucw34r">Context</h1> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-hasiie">I was born and raised in Hong Kong for over 15 years, and would consider myself
a native Cantonese speaker. However, if you asked me to physically write Chinese
characters in order to save a cute little puppy🐶… it would unfortunately not
make it.</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-2g5nfy">Why is that? Why can read, speak and listen to Chinese perfectly fine but have
such a low grasp on writing. I’ve read the
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Remembrance_of_Earth%27s_Past" rel="nofollow">Remembrance of Earth’s Past Trilogy</a>
and other books with no clear issues. So <strong>why is the physical act of writing
impossible for me?</strong> This activity seems to require a different collection of
memory and a different way of learning.</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-i3rmwp">A further argument is that since I can function in Chinese, maybe the physical
act of writing is a remnant of the past.</p> <h1 data-svelte-h="svelte-1x0bd17">What is going on when I try to write Chinese characters?</h1> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-fhmnod">If I can express ideas verbally, shouldn’t I be able to write them as well? This
is what I do in English. This is what I do in English. You can tell in my tone
here that I approach writing in a casual, speaking-like manner. However, when I
take pen to paper in Chinese, my mind goes totally blank and I can’t even piece
together a proper sentence.</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-1fo09l4">An <strong>incorrect</strong> analogy is forgetting how to spell a word in English. In
English, by pronouncing the word I can probably fudge it and make it 90% there.
In Chinese, it’s more like trying to do a life-like painting of a person you
know. It’s clear as day what this person looks like but when you start, you
realise all the detail is not there. I often can start by trying to imagine
reading the character in a book and attempting to replicate it. For most
characters that I don’t recall, my success rate would be less than 20%.</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-1ou3e4y">The size of the gap between my reading versus my writing.</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-tg9qas">An obvious reason is that Chinese is a logogram writing system. This is where
writing is based on logos/symbols/characters and not based phonetically. This
means knowing how to say a word has almost no bearing on how to write it. I say
almost as there are usually 部首 that do guide pronunciation.</p> <h1 data-svelte-h="svelte-1dhq7vr">Is Typing the same as writing?</h1> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-10skc85">I type using Pinyin. Pinyin is the phonetic conversion of a character
constructed using the alphabet. Pinyin sprouted around the 50s and is taught
around the world. There are other input methods using an array of different
philosophies like the order of strokes.</p> <blockquote data-svelte-h="svelte-15cxvcs"><p>Using Pinyin’s 2 has core strengths. One, I can sound the word out. Two, I can
use the keyboard assistance to read the potential options.</p></blockquote> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-u40ugz"><strong>To me, writing is a way to communicate ideas to readers.</strong></p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-1ngoa9f">Whether I write those words or type those words doesn’t seem too critical. I
wouldn’t write this article on paper first and then re-type it out, and the the
reader also wouldn’t know/care.</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-pfvv0d">If the goal is to convey information to many people, typing might even be a more
important skill of the language to learn. To further push this established
premise, I tried learning Japanese for around 3 months. My teacher never once
brought up teaching me how to write Kanji. It seemed to be a given that I would
learn how to type instead.</p> <h1 data-svelte-h="svelte-1hoxlhz">Conclusion</h1> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-1ftkuo2">My final conclusion is that learning to physically write is no longer an
important facet of languages. The design of prose and command of vocabulary are
vital to good writing.</p>]]></content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>My computer setup</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/my_computer_setup"/>
<id>https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/my_computer_setup</id>
<published>2024-06-07T00:00:00.000Z</published>
<updated>2024-06-07T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p data-svelte-h="svelte-14dh4os">To put things into context, my primary purposes for a computer is to program, watch videos and play video games. That’s pretty much it and accounts for all I need a computer from.</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-1g6yfix">I prefer a setup with minimal fuss and can be flexible enough to adapt to either new technologies and games.</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-fp6hj1">In this post I aim to cover a few of the choices I’ve made and why I’ve made them.</p> <h2 data-svelte-h="svelte-9h4468">My hardware</h2> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-1wbjhxz">Currently in my disposable are:</p> <ul data-svelte-h="svelte-au8lji"><li>PC <a href="https://uk.pcpartpicker.com/list/6pc9MV" rel="nofollow">specs</a></li> <li>Laptop <a href="https://www.asus.com/laptops/for-home/vivobook/vivobook-s14-s410/techspec/" rel="nofollow">specs</a></li> <li>Work Laptop</li></ul> <h3 data-svelte-h="svelte-1l1tj2e">OS</h3> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-hl2dl8">I’ve been a long time user of Windows but am always aware of possible benefits of switching to Linux/Mac Os. As I don’t have money to kill, Mac was always out of the question. There are also potential drawbacks mainly because there will be games that are only compatible with Windows.</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-7zxj8i">For linux, there is much better support for development tools. Tools like pyenv, bash, docker, just work natively. Even just base path manipulation is much easier without <a href="https://www.fileside.app/blog/2023-03-17_windows-file-paths/" rel="nofollow">weird windows paths</a>.</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-v6uce9">There is the possibility to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Multi-booting" rel="nofollow">dual boot</a> but that seems like pain to manage.</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-cz6nhu">To mitigate it, WSL looks to be the best of both worlds. It’s support looks to be a priority for microsoft and there’s been consistent releases and good guides on getting setup.</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-su59gj">I’ve used WSL now on my home PC and work laptop.</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-11cka99">Gotchas. WSL can be slow, uses loads of memory and sometimes freezes.</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-kc7giu">For my personal laptop, I’m somewhat limited by the hardware. It’s been use for 6 years now and the battery is dropping off. Everything performs slow on that laptop making it hardly productive. I only use it when I go to a cafe to write or program (so no games). To breath some new life into it, I decided to install linux mint onto it. It’s been much more responsive and the battery life seems to be better (probably due to the wipe not the os).</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-gm3u8v">There are many tools in</p> <ul data-svelte-h="svelte-qu6033"><li><p>OS</p> <ul><li>WSL</li> <li>Linux Mint!</li></ul></li> <li><p>Code Editor</p> <ul><li>VSCode + extensions</li></ul></li> <li><p>Env Management</p> <ul><li>Pyenv</li> <li>Nvm</li> <li>Poetry</li> <li>Pnpm</li></ul></li></ul> <h1 data-svelte-h="svelte-1d1kbfu">IDE</h1> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-1duzwzo">I started out programming with Eclipse on the Oxygen release. I used the PyDev extension and was building a little Selenium application to automate some UI testing. I also tried out Atom to help write some python automation scripts. Both tools felt like they weren’t providing me with a lot. They had poor ui and is limited to someone who just want’s to build stuff.</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-h3i2xr">I started using VScode and its just much more beginner friendly, more multi-language friendly and has tons of community support. It now also works well with WSL (both being microsoft).</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-z52y26">Very recently, I’ve been inspired to learn Vim and started to use th VScodeVim extension. It’s worked quite well so far and it is always nice to learn a new skill.</p> <h2 data-svelte-h="svelte-13n9cvh">Environment managers</h2> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-1sqktd7">I primarily program in Python (AI) or Javascript (Apps).</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-18827j4">For python, one of the main issues when trying to access multiple different repos is the python version compatability. Later versions of python have features the old versions do not. Managing python versions is super annoying and installing all of them and switching between them is not easy out of the box. A tool I’ve been using is Pyenv which allows you to switch python versions very easily.</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-gtmuaq">For node, I use the equivalently helpful nvm tool.</p> <h2 data-svelte-h="svelte-1abh3pa">Package managers</h2> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-1f6flto">The pacakge manager for python I use is Poetry. It provides version locking and venv handling. It’s a pretty tried and tested tool. PDM is the new comer on the block but I have not tried it yet.</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-178zp9p">For node, I use pnpm (a drop in for npm).
There’s bun and yarn too to try but again I haven’t done the work.</p>]]></content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Ongoing musings</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/ongoing_musings"/>
<id>https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/ongoing_musings</id>
<published>2024-01-01T00:00:00.000Z</published>
<updated>2024-12-01T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
<content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1 data-svelte-h="svelte-hlcavb">Random thoughts</h1> <h3 data-svelte-h="svelte-1w4ukkf">Is writing any language important in our generation?✅</h3> <ul data-svelte-h="svelte-23x2sc"><li>Fluency of language</li> <li>Reading vs writing vs listening vs speaking</li> <li>Writing versus typing</li> <li>Can there be a universal language?</li></ul> <h3 data-svelte-h="svelte-x4n2h3">~~ How good is Feng shui 風水?~~</h3> <ul data-svelte-h="svelte-1gumwlo"><li><del>Is Feng shui based on good UX?</del></li> <li><del>Who still uses feng shui?</del></li></ul> <h3 data-svelte-h="svelte-ogtpt4">When did people start sleeping on their backs?✅</h3> <ul data-svelte-h="svelte-1cj8jip"><li>Invention of the pillow?</li></ul> <h3 data-svelte-h="svelte-1yyg738">Why is most programming languages english?</h3> <ul data-svelte-h="svelte-g457ia"><li>Information density of languages</li> <li>History of programming</li> <li>Exciting languages that uses different languages</li></ul> <h3 data-svelte-h="svelte-5nb3fz">Factfulness now?</h3> <ul data-svelte-h="svelte-sc29gn"><li>Factfulness was an interesting book</li> <li>How true has it been in the last ten years?</li> <li>Will it stay try?</li></ul> <h3 data-svelte-h="svelte-vjg9">Experiment on waxy breakdown of garlic</h3> <ul data-svelte-h="svelte-az2z02"><li>Waxy breakdown of Garlic</li> <li>Other types of garlic breakdown</li> <li>Sets of experiments</li> <li>Reproducibility?</li> <li>Strains? - Putting my bio labskills to the test</li></ul> <h3 data-svelte-h="svelte-18kvit9">My coding setup</h3> <ul data-svelte-h="svelte-b981mt"><li>OS<ul><li>WSL!</li> <li>Linux Mint!</li></ul></li> <li>Code Editor<ul><li>VSCode + extensions</li></ul></li> <li>Python Env Management<ul><li>Pyenv</li> <li>Poetry</li></ul></li> <li>Bash setup</li></ul> <h3 data-svelte-h="svelte-1ydyurf">Baking AI / Receipes AI</h3> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-1lweux1">An AI taht generates new recipes</p> <h3 data-svelte-h="svelte-2ujcsp">UK health labels</h3> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-r7tdjo">What does the health labels mean, and why some has colours.</p> <h3 data-svelte-h="svelte-1p8e6aq">The stagnation of Travelling</h3> <ul data-svelte-h="svelte-hztik2"><li>Travelling when young</li> <li>Travelling when older</li> <li>Travelling or vactioning</li></ul> <h3 data-svelte-h="svelte-1db5une">How to ideate?</h3> <ul data-svelte-h="svelte-rkl3up"><li>Ideas that are fun</li> <li>Ideas that make money</li></ul> <h3 data-svelte-h="svelte-5jwni1">Anonymity or Named?</h3> <ul data-svelte-h="svelte-1l8d6cf"><li>Github</li> <li>Blog</li> <li>Skin in the game</li></ul> <h3 data-svelte-h="svelte-o4sh2c">Building a new typeface</h3> <ul data-svelte-h="svelte-jyg0xp"><li>How to create a typeface?</li> <li>Introducing my own typeface</li></ul> <h3 data-svelte-h="svelte-1erx15">Information hierarchy</h3> <ul data-svelte-h="svelte-xar8zb"><li>Spectrum of watching, listening, reading, speaking and writing.</li> <li>Getting information to creating information</li></ul> <h1 data-svelte-h="svelte-1apo7ge">Fiction</h1> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-1y8kwve">City of clouds</p> <ul data-svelte-h="svelte-1h22gwx"><li>Cloud Emperor</li> <li>Molten core with a dense cloud</li> <li>Cloud archeticture</li> <li>Flora of vines and flowers</li></ul> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-1w0urt2">Ride to somwhere ✅</p>]]></content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Pickpockets operate at this station.</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/pickpockets_operate_at_this_station"/>
<id>https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/pickpockets_operate_at_this_station</id>
<published>2024-01-01T00:00:00.000Z</published>
<updated>2024-01-01T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p data-svelte-h="svelte-1hckrum">This phrase is played across London tube stations. The nonchalant and robotic tone of the broadcast sounds as though the pickpocketers simply work at the station. In line with the “See it, say it and sort it” and “No Staring” posters, it brings a looming inevitability that hooliganism is always by our side.</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-1jngayd">How do these safety reminders give Londoners and visitors a sense of security? If nothing else, it adds to the pervasiveness of lawlessness and keenly suggests that the system cannot protect you. Fend for yourselves lest you get robbed. This distasteful tone underlines London’s coldness and inhumanness. As a community, we seem to need an active message that these things are wrong and to help others.</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-vy5fh8">Right and wrong is lost and the common respect for a society is gone. The rubbish found inside the tube and station is also absolutely appalling. Random bottles and food packaging are just lying on any possible flat surface, including the floor, seats and handrails. Chewing gum everywhere. Instead of convincing good citizens to confront, we need to build a strong guilt system against petty crimes and behaviours.</p>]]></content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Ride to somewhere</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/ride_to_somewhere"/>
<id>https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/ride_to_somewhere</id>
<published>2024-01-01T00:00:00.000Z</published>
<updated>2024-01-01T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
<content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1 data-svelte-h="svelte-1mf2mbm">Ride to somewhere</h1> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-xbuc6a">I open my eyes. I’m on a bus. It’s packed and stuffy. The people around me speak a language I do not understand. The window on my left shows a scenery of shrubs and more shrubs. My right shows a barren rocky landscape.</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-1twu8av">A gentleman is sitting next to me. His cane is lodged between his legs, and he wears a mismatched tweed suit and beige chino pants. I asked him where we were and where we were heading but got nothing more than a shrug. There is no information about where the bus is going.</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-1z78q8">I try to relax. The bus stops every half a minute with many people getting on and off. A mom with a stroller gets on and off at the same station. This must be the wrong bus for her. The twists and turns of the journey make me want to vomit. I check my backpack only to find a blank notebook, without a pen.</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-gsxutm">I close my eyes and drift into an uneasy sleep. As I wake up, I realise I’m still on the bus, heading somewhere.</p>]]></content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Waxy breakdown of garlic and experimental design.</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/waxy_breakdown"/>
<id>https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/waxy_breakdown</id>
<published>2024-10-07T00:00:00.000Z</published>
<updated>2024-12-07T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p data-svelte-h="svelte-195qycq"><a href="https://bpp.oregonstate.edu/sites/agscid7/files/bpp/attachments/waxy-breakdown-of-garlic-feb-7-mlp.pdf" rel="nofollow">Waxy breakdown</a> of garlic is a phenomenon where garlic can go translucent and yellow. The pyruvic acid levels of the garlic also reduces, lowering its pugency and has a softer texture.
It’s considered a disease? but
It’s different to black garlic which is fermented.</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-1m6mtjz">I’ve had it happen a few times to my stash of garlic. I was initially weary about using it as it look’s off, but once I did, I really enjoyed it. It’s taste is much more mellow letting me use it more sparingly. The softer texture also makes it smearable allowing it to be easily added to a marinade or paste.</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-1p59vzv">It’s described as a defect by some sources but I didn’t really find any fault in it.</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-1on6j3x">What really interests me is that although Garlic is a main seasoning in a chef’s arsenal, there is relatively little research on how and why it develops.</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-1nk43nx">Variables:
Heat
Humidity
Time
Sunlight
Closed container?
Salt?
Sugar?
Peeled vs Blubs vs untouched</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-1x96sjc">Proxy setup:
I unfortunately do not have precise temperature or humidity guages, nore have thav con trols for them. In their stead I’m using situations that are common in my hosue.</p> <ul data-svelte-h="svelte-i8nvdx"><li>China(orange) - Spain(blue)</li> <li>Fridge/Cabinent/Sun</li> <li>Bagged/left out</li> <li>Broken - Bulb</li></ul> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-l8oqaw"><strong>Cabinent</strong>
China - Cabinent - Out - Bulb
China - Cabinent - Bagged - Broken
China - Cabinent - Bagged - Bulb</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-1iswwx">Spain - Cabinent - Bagged - Broken
Spain - Cabinent - Out - Broken
Spain - Cabinent - Out - Bulb</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-1072bvy"><strong>Sun</strong>
China - Sun - Out - Bulb
China - Sun - Bagged - Broken
China - Sun - Out - Broken</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-17vh8ej">Spain - Sun - Out - Bulb
Spain - Sun - Bagged - Broken
Spain - Sun - Out - Broken</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-14myanm"><strong>Fridge</strong>
China - Fridge - Out - Bulb
China - Fridge - Bagged - Broken
China - Fridge - Out - Broken</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-1ptvwng">Spain - Fridge - Bagged - Bulb
Spain - Fridge - Bagged - Broken</p> <h2 data-svelte-h="svelte-1mb7uyw">As of 21-11-2024</h2> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-l8oqaw"><strong>Cabinent</strong>
China - Cabinent - Out - Bulb
China - Cabinent - Bagged - Broken
China - Cabinent - Bagged - Bulb</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-rgo71">Spain - Cabinent - Bagged - Broken - 1/10
Spain - Cabinent - Out - Broken
Spain - Cabinent - Out - Bulb</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-1072bvy"><strong>Sun</strong>
China - Sun - Out - Bulb
China - Sun - Bagged - Broken
China - Sun - Out - Broken</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-17vh8ej">Spain - Sun - Out - Bulb
Spain - Sun - Bagged - Broken
Spain - Sun - Out - Broken</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-14myanm"><strong>Fridge</strong>
China - Fridge - Out - Bulb
China - Fridge - Bagged - Broken
China - Fridge - Out - Broken</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-1ptvwng">Spain - Fridge - Bagged - Bulb
Spain - Fridge - Bagged - Broken</p> <h2 data-svelte-h="svelte-16dpqyz">As of 03-12-2024</h2> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-13xkqgx">no change</p> <h2 data-svelte-h="svelte-58us0s">As of 06-12-2024</h2> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-13xkqgx">no change</p> <h2 data-svelte-h="svelte-1mb7uyw">As of 21-11-2024</h2> <h2 data-svelte-h="svelte-ofjygt">Design of expeirments</h2> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-riz0st">I currently work at a bio-tech startup and a statistical approach to analyse variation based on factors is through Design of Experiments (DOE).</p> <h3 data-svelte-h="svelte-148thpj">What is DOE?</h3> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-1mqlii3">A famous example of DOE is the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lady_tasting_tea" rel="nofollow">lady tasting tea</a> experiment done by Ronald Fischer. In it, Ronald faces a lady who proposes she can tell the difference of if <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=InWGdojtWys" rel="nofollow">milk is poured first or tea is poured first</a>.</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-yu12a3">To test this claim, Ronald devised the null hypothesis that she cannot determine between the two. He then asks what is the minimum about of tests to conduct to be confident enough for.
Im it he decides making 8 teas is good, 4 with milk first and 4 with milk second. Why 8?
All possible combinations of these 8 are 70. Based on pure chance, getting it all right has one possible combination. This sets the experiment with signifcance level of 1/70.</p> <h3 data-svelte-h="svelte-4xq7w7">Why DOE?</h3> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-13qipsn">Experiments are expensive. As a sciencitist you would like to conduct the least amount while preserving reliability and information space that it provides. Leveraging statistics help define how confident you can be and optimise for certain factors to test.</p> <h3 data-svelte-h="svelte-3w3ce1">How does DOE work?</h3> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-1ev6ck1">One can extend the above to more factors and even analyse <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Confounding" rel="nofollow">confounding factors</a>. The search/test space gets exponentially greater as you will need to test much more combinations.</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-lp5sev">Factors also have levels and their relationships can also be non-linear.</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-1m4mr1t">Temp
Humidity</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-x0n6lr">Implementing DOE in our experiment.</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-c221d3"><a href="https://www.ipt.us.com/produce-inspection-resources/inspectors-blog/defect-identification/garlic-waxy-breakdown" rel="nofollow">https://www.ipt.us.com/produce-inspection-resources/inspectors-blog/defect-identification/garlic-waxy-breakdown</a></p>]]></content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Are beds just a capatilist</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/why_do_we_sleep_on_our_backs"/>
<id>https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/why_do_we_sleep_on_our_backs</id>
<published>2024-12-01T00:00:00.000Z</published>
<updated>2024-12-01T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p data-svelte-h="svelte-1l8hc5t">Sleeping is a large part of our lives. It accounts for a third of our time on earth (albeit being unconscious). Sleep enables us to rest our muscles, removes toxins from our brain and retains memories. It’s essential to intelligent life and almost all animals sleep. This technique of recovery requires no training and is essential to our young. Although the origins of sleep and dreams are still a mystery in the evolution timeline, there little doubt of its importance.</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-1o2ukgj">Personally as a ploy to improve my sleep, I’ve tried in the past to adapt my sleep as close to what our ancestors did. This meant <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polyphasic_sleep" rel="nofollow">polyastic sleep</a>. It never worked for me as it rarely fitted the reality of an 9-6 job.</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-dg6s47">But .. what if … I trade my soft bed for a hard surface?</p> <h2 data-svelte-h="svelte-1ybzb2d">How do we sleep?</h2> <h3 data-svelte-h="svelte-a6r7t4">Different types of sleeping positions</h3> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-1w98io3">Before looking too deeply into beds, let’s take a detour on how we sleep. There are different types of sleeping positions.</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-18p36ia">Some sleep on their back (supine like me) and some sleep on their side. There are also those out there that sleep on their front. These positions seem to come from habit and are ingrained into how we sleep. Though most people stick to one position at the start of their sleep, we <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC5677378/" rel="nofollow">tend to move about</a>. A common treatment to enforce side sleeping is through a <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2762713/" rel="nofollow">tennis ball</a> (to stop you from rolling) but the compliance is low.</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-qtz9du">Is there a right way to sleep then? The research points out that most people (54%) sleep on the side but correlation vs causation of sleep quality and position is less understood. The main studies I found have small samples 30.</p> <h2 data-svelte-h="svelte-jwo456">When were the bed and pillows invented?</h2> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-x4rjpr">When did we start needing a pillow? It seems strange that our head somewhat dangles on our shoulders. Especially when lying flat our neck and tummy, two quite vulnerable parts of our body are exposed.</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-18127ui">At a <a href="https://wellcomecollection.org/exhibitions/Y8VNbhEAAPJM-oki" rel="nofollow">Milk</a> exhibition at the Wellcome Collection, I saw milk described as a pure marketing capitalist ploy which was engaged during and post the Second World War. A staple in our diets is mostly brought upon by companies looking to sell it. 65% per cent of people in the world are lactose intolerant, so perhaps it should be called lactose tolerance for these outliers.</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-1u1kpru">Is it a similar case here? Are pillows and a soft bed a construction of capitalism?</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-29x907">There is <a href="https://phys.org/news/2020-08-years-humans-beds.html" rel="nofollow">evidence</a> that prehistoric humans 200,000 years ago already slept on grass-laden beds. Egyptians had wooden beds and also explored using pillows and headrests. During Roman times, the mattresses on beds got more sophisticated with hay or wool and even feathers stuffed in them. These beds were a step up from sleeping on the floor, keeping insects away and providing an insulated base. More recently there are Kang beds from China which are heated underneath and Tatamis from Japan which are matted flooring used for sleeping.</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-1io9yw1">The main benefits of a bed is to stay away from vermin and keep warm.</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-1ck0gx9">In modern times, beds definitely became softer and softer. As beds get softer it raises a question whether it’s improving our sleep.</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-fjcpz2">Beds became more and more widespread</p> <h3 data-svelte-h="svelte-16bcd3b">Do other animals sleep on beds?</h3> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-ugkeh7">A separate angle of attack is to look at our animals. Dog for example sleeps fine on hard surfaces and so do most non-domesticated animals. A monkey sleeps hugging a firm tree 10 metres off the ground. Many birds have a mechanism called <a href="https://simple.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tendon_locking" rel="nofollow">Tedon Locking</a>, which locks in their feet so that they don’t fall off. I don’t think I’ll find that exceptionally comfortable and safe and indeed there are described cases of these animals falling off.</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-kjsepg">This shows a support for not needing to have beds. However, in the same vein, most animals don’t wear clothes and those seem to be quite helpful against the cold. Tools define the man and the bed could be an impactful one.</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-ks2a1s">There’s evidence that our sleep is different and much <a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/evan.21464" rel="nofollow">deeper than our close ancestors</a>. We sleep less and have better intellect. This points to be a</p> <h3 data-svelte-h="svelte-d7kqkf">Conclusion</h3> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-42q5l0">The wider spread of beds</p>]]></content>
</entry>
</feed>
