<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<title>Chris L's blog about things</title>
<id>https://lcmchris.github.io/</id>
<link rel="alternate" href="https://lcmchris.github.io/"/>
<link rel="self" href="https://lcmchris.github.io/rss.xml"/>
<updated>2025-12-16T23:29:15.468Z</updated>
<author>
<name>Chris L</name>
</author>
<entry>
<title>Get food with your colleagues</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/get_food_with_your_colleagues"/>
<id>https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/get_food_with_your_colleagues</id>
<published>2025-12-16T00:00:00.000Z</published>
<updated>2025-12-16T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
<content type="html"><![CDATA[<!--[--><p>Getting food with your colleagues is important.</p> <p>I believe a core part of work is knowing the people you work with. Not in a casual, friendly sense but to understand this person’s style, structured and way of thinking.</p> <p>The road to the restaurant or the local supermarket for a meal deal is perfect for this. In this small slit of time, you’re at work but not fully at work. This I find is the best opportunity to chat and get a truer sense of what the other thinks of certain ideas. It’s a rare noncommittal, low effort, high trust environment to talk about the project or design. You can be much more playful with your words and explore thoughts that you feel inappropriate in a wider official setting. Nothing in the time is set in stone. There is a certain freedom to it.</p> <p>It is also, of course, a great time to talk bs and build camaraderie. In an age of remote work and WFH, I hope this human touch does not get lost.</p> <img src="/_app/immutable/assets/16_art.B_FBtAq5.jpg" alt="Benoit Blanc: Day 16"/><!--]-->]]></content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>On interesting writers</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/on_interesting_people"/>
<id>https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/on_interesting_people</id>
<published>2025-12-15T00:00:00.000Z</published>
<updated>2025-12-15T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
<content type="html"><![CDATA[<!--[--><p>On interesting people who have written.</p> <h3>Paul Graham</h3> <p>I first engaged in his writing in 2022. On a trip to Gran Canaria, I downloaded everyone of his essays and binged read all of it. I’ve heard of YCombinator before this and loved the basis of a merit based startup fund. His writings are fairly widespread but generally centred around, startups, writing, and making things. Possibly my favourite piece is <a href="https://paulgraham.com/genius.html" rel="nofollow">genius</a>. It explains that a fundamental ingredient that’s generally missed on genius is the importance of the topic. Being a die-hard trainspotter is unfortunately, unlikely to make you do great work. A greater insight is to find this obsessive nature. His latest reiterates the importance of creating things in <a href="https://paulgraham.com/do.html" rel="nofollow">What to do</a>. There is something missing is his ideas though. I think he links happiness and goals directly to his metric of success. Creating a startup or innovation is important, but I don’t think it’s broadly applicable to everyone in the world. Trainspotting is probably not the most important thing out there, but the joy and happiness it brings to the individual could be immense.</p> <h3>Jordan Peterson (PRE-2018)</h3> <p>I think it’s generally recognised that Jordan Peterson is nowadays, a highly controversial figure. Back when I first listened to him pre 2018, he had a calm nature with a focus on reason. His famous interview with Cathay Newman inspired me to be <code>very very very careful with my words</code> and back up opinions with fact. Now that happiness and reason has turned to fame and resentfulness. I also liked his position on the equality of opportunity and to regardless push yourself to do what you want.</p> <h3>Christopher Nolan</h3> <p>Nolan may not have written essays, but many of his films are written by him and his brother. My favourite film of all time is <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Prestige_(film)" rel="nofollow">The Prestige</a>. It’s layering of mystery, the twist (or turn) and strong characters in the film is truly masterful. Amongst his others, the standout usage of time as a concept and the non-linearity plots shows the depth of his thought process. I care less for his films like Oppenheimer, Dunkirk, even batman…which are more linear. Whilst beautiful, they lack the narrative spark the nonlinear ones do. The ability to weave intrigue and mystery against a nonlinear timeline via flashbacks or time travel sets him apart.</p> <h3>Murakami</h3> <p>I have read some of Murakami’s novel’s. They are always an experience novelist as a vocation. A key inspiring fact about Murakami is he only started writing in his thirties. In Novelist as a vocation, he described his 20s He spent most of his time hosting a jazz bar/ café, in what seemed wasted years. It was not his passion and the medial work seemed to have beaten on his soul. But, once he found writing and picked it up, he never looked back and now has become one of the biggest translated Japanese writers. This story helped make me do more things, you can never know where your true passion lies and also when It can erupt.
His style is described as magical realism. I find his settings whimsical, impressionistic and abstract. It has a lot of inner monologues of characters giving you a close connection between you and them. I do find though that the weird sex scenes take me out of the story. It often leaves me baffled and I feel it’s unneeded. But whose to say, Tarantino’s gore in his films can also seem unnecessary or complete, depending on the viewer.</p><!--]-->]]></content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>About taking risks</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/taking_risks"/>
<id>https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/taking_risks</id>
<published>2025-12-12T00:00:00.000Z</published>
<updated>2025-12-12T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
<content type="html"><![CDATA[<!--[--><h2>What is risk taking</h2> <p>In this day and age, taking risks is what all the cool kids do. Everyone wants to be a founder or be part of a start up or run a crypto exchange. Even going for big tech earning 6 figures is considered a <code>safe choice</code>. Why has this point of view become the norm? I think that just having general wealth being a lot higher has helped. Being born in a first world country nowadays is already a big advantage. You will be unlikely to suffer from total poverty where even finding food and shelter is hard. This inherently reduces the size of risk people are taking. The rich kid not working a mundane job is not really a risk taker as his downside is nil.</p> <p>In my definition:</p> <p>Big risk = Only if you have a big penalty on failure. The penalty also have to be meaningful. I think the range of middle class has expanded. Middle classes has a decent house, car and can afford 1 holiday a year. With quite a wide range of income, there isn’t much of a material difference.</p> <p>In this definition then, maybe our risk appetite hasn’t changed much as losing is just not as what it used to be.</p> <h2>Is being a risk taker trained or learnt?</h2> <p>If being a risk taker is desirable, is it a skill to learn or is it just an innate attribute you are born with? In my opinion it actually depends on ignorance. As a child, when you have little experiences, you would skateboard, jump into swimming pools and in general be a bit more fearless. This fearlessness or lack of long-term calculations, can help in being more risky. Say for quitting a stable job for a riskier startup option, it helps if you do not factor in all the possible outcomes. Blocking of the high probability of failure</p> <p>…</p> <img src="/_app/immutable/assets/12_1_art.DbVUuAX1.jpg" width="200" alt="Sketches"/> <img src="/_app/immutable/assets/12_2_art.BG1Rxsz6.jpg" width="200" alt="Sketches"/> <img src="/_app/immutable/assets/12_3_art.C76e1qIR.jpg" width="200" alt="Sketches"/> <img src="/_app/immutable/assets/12_4_art.DXkBO5lh.jpeg" width="200" alt="Sketches"/><!--]-->]]></content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Review of Expedition 33</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/expedition_33"/>
<id>https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/expedition_33</id>
<published>2025-12-09T00:00:00.000Z</published>
<updated>2025-12-09T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
<content type="html"><![CDATA[<!--[--><p>I have been hooked on Expedition 33 for the last few days. I learnt about this game from the Brandon Sanderson podcast on ‘Video games’. In the comments, many have suggested him to play this as the lead writer of the game is a fan. Many of the world-building came from both the wheel of time as well.</p> <h3>Things I disliked</h3> <p>Let’s start off with things I dislike.</p> <p>The camera movement can be super disorientating. Especially enemy moves with a long wind up and almost cut-scene like action. It makes some fights unwieldy and a bit annoying (paintress fight). There is an option to disable the camera movement but then if the attack is off-screen, you won’t be able to even see it.</p> <p>Lack of numbers (levels and damage). There are certain areas of the map which although accessible, is outrageous over leveled. It can be interesting to go into an impossible fight but I have had this experience too many times where my first attack tickles an enemy. I can’t even surrender so I have to quietly let it kill me. Having a little level indicator might be a nice feature to let me understand which enemies I should or should not attempt. The other lack is the damage numbers on abilities. For the hardcore gamers, I know I can respec and test every combo to see which does more damage, but wouldn’t it be nicer if I know what the exact damage numbers are instead of just <code>low</code> <code>medium</code> and <code>high</code>? It’s also not correct. There’s a notorious ability that does insane damage but only described as <code>medium</code>. Having the raw numbers can allow us theory craft! My feeling is it is a</p> <p>Lack of maps. This is super annoying. Half the time I’m so lost and just following some vague idea of a straight line. In an area called the Costal Cave (it’s a under water cave area) I was so lost I had to look up a guide and this was just a beginner area. Shouldn’t all these past expeditions leave maps? That seems like an important thing to do! In many levels, I would spend time in circles before I can see where it wants me to go. In most cases I can’t even tell if it’s the right way or not.</p> <h3>Things I liked</h3> <p>Clearly the main focus of the game is the story. Unlike Souls games, there is a difficultly setting which helps any player progress the storyline. I think the twist was very satisfying and it’s one of those stories where there’s very little holes in it. I do slightly feel the original gimmick of <code>Every year everyone in that age dies</code> is not fully utilised especially since the story begins on year 33. It might have been nice to flash back on the voice recordings to different years both in the expedition and the actual city. There was only the one Gommage. It is a lot of story already to cover though so perhaps the writer thought the whole expedition dynamic was enough. But I do find it slightly unbelievable when the Gommage on 34 had maybe 10 deaths and the forgotten battlefield had over 10,000. The world building of luminere is also just right. There’s enough realism (paris) to help you make connections whilst dreamy enough to give you mystery.</p> <p>The turn based gameplay is fun. I haven’t played jrpgs before so this is a new genre for me. Before starting, I would’ve thought I’d hated it. But the mixture of cool abilities and interesting combos, I had a pretty good time! I ended up not really using Monoco and Sciel, I think I was too attached to the core trio to switch. Each character’s gimmick is very different so it might’ve been nice to have more opportunities to be forced into playing them.</p> <p>The music and voice acting was incredible. It’s quite rare that I would find a game where I am happy to sit and just listen to the soundtrack. The other notable game that a sick soundtrack is Maple story. These are music pieces that can stand on its own and with a dark, emotional, grief filled story, it worked fabulously. Here’s a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Y17JlC1rBoc" rel="nofollow">live version</a> that is again, just incredible.</p> <h3>Final thoughts</h3> <p>I’m definitely looking forward to anything this game developer releases. It’s a unique experience and a whirlwind of 5-days of playing. I hope they would create a sequel or expand more on the writers.</p><!--]-->]]></content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>List of potential business ideas</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/list_of_business_ideas"/>
<id>https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/list_of_business_ideas</id>
<published>2025-12-07T00:00:00.000Z</published>
<updated>2025-12-07T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
<content type="html"><![CDATA[<!--[--><p>I have yet to give up on my startup dreams.
Here’s a list of potential business ideas for this season.</p> <h3><em>Tried</em></h3> <p>Meeting optimiser
AI based Smart homes
AI Font generation</p> <h3>Potential</h3> <ul><li>Booking platform for Dentist</li> <li></li></ul> <p>TBC</p><!--]-->]]></content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Trying to get better at portraiture; Learning as an Adult</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/getting_better_at_portraiture"/>
<id>https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/getting_better_at_portraiture</id>
<published>2025-12-06T00:00:00.000Z</published>
<updated>2025-12-06T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
<content type="html"><![CDATA[<!--[--><p>As you can tell, my portraiture is not very good.</p> <img src="/_app/immutable/assets/06_art.Bz6JqWkT.jpg" alt="Female practice" width="400"/> <p>In this Advent of Art, I want to change that.</p> <p>My understanding of the facial distances seems to always be a bit off, leading to an uncanny face.
Working on something you aren’t good at is something you do when you’re young. Can an old dog still learn new tricks? Can passion and work triumph over a lack a talent?</p> <h3>Adult classes for learning</h3> <p>Aside from portraiture, I’ve also been playing a bit more badminton. I did a lot of classes when I was little and can play alright. Whilst a bit older and wiser now, I’m learning technique more methodically and less just pure muscle memory. Understanding the movements has helped in making me play better. I can honestly say I’m better than the 15 year old me. I didn’t learn more through classes but it’s not for trying! Finding feasible adult classes has been quite tough. Most clubs and teachers gear themselves to teach younglings. It’s a matter of fact that the market for adult classes is small, most learners are young or tailored to parents.</p> <h3>Back to portraiture, Rembrandt.</h3> <p>For portraiture, an artist that I really like is Rembrandt. His high contrasted shadows adds an ominous atmosphere to the depiction and builds emotions to the image. From the Dutch Golden Age, he also produced many (~40) <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Self-portraits_by_Rembrandt" rel="nofollow">self-portraits</a> from when he was young to old. His own soul, life, and feeling at the time is poured onto the canvas, almost like an artistic performance. It’s clear to me that he uses these as an experiment, as a diary and as a strong learning tool. I particularly enjoy his older portraits. It has the most texture. For my learning journey on this Advent of Art, I’ll be primarily trying drawing self-portraits and perhaps also my partner.</p><!--]-->]]></content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Beyond time</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/draft"/>
<id>https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/draft</id>
<published>2025-12-05T00:00:00.000Z</published>
<updated>2025-12-05T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
<content type="html"><![CDATA[<!--[--><p>Angelo is swimming in a lido.</p> <blockquote><blockquote><p>Teleportation device
Discombopulation and reconstruction.
Daily usage and is common. What happens to the organic matter left behind?
Travelling the universe
Human backups
how are memories stored in our brains
Actual cloning is prohibited. Due to the widespread abuse of labour and slavery.
Teleporter is a 3d biochemical printer
Reporter scandal on constructed memorys ‘implanted ads’</p></blockquote></blockquote><!--]-->]]></content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Reflection on starting a business</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/starting_a_business"/>
<id>https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/starting_a_business</id>
<published>2025-12-05T00:00:00.000Z</published>
<updated>2025-12-05T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
<content type="html"><![CDATA[<!--[--><p>As a young boy, I was told I had an entrepreneurial spirit and I like to make money. A funny and repeatable story that my mom constantly repeats is how I manage to sell an empty water bottle to a fellow student in my secondary school for $10, more than when it was full. She needed it for a craft project and as I was the only empty bottle owner, I could charge monopoly prices. I think my connection to me liking money is because of my early interest in the stock markets. I use to think I’m one of the chosen stock prediction gurus and can time buying the highest and the lowest. These embedded ideologies led me to always want to take more risks and start something of my own. I recall at 21, when I started a new job that by 25 I need to start my own business. My early twenties flew by. During it, I worked on a few fun projects, including a website to help UK residents find the optimal driving test centre, an algorithm to figure out when to cross the streets in New York gridlike structure. Perhaps my favourite was my flappy bird game in VR. None of these really fufilled my desire to start a business. So at the end of age 25, I made a risky decision of leaving my stable data analyst role and go into the wild for 1 year to test out my many ideas. I was really into smart homes back then and thought applying machine learning to the home control pattern would be a big leap. This led me to create TheSillyHome. It begun as a for-profit project but I could not find traction in enough users to share information for training. Then it morphed into a more open-source project. I found how hard it is to actually get people to pay you for your product and also how tough the open-source community is to their founders. There’s no slack cut out just because it’s free. Perhaps, they demand even more. After 6 months (this seems to be a repeating offense), my passion for the project wilted away. The next project I tried was a meeting management tool. Everyone hates meetings right? Why not automate/track meeting time more efficiently. Turns out tracking although useful does not actually have any actionable insights. Meetings are meetings, just like taxes are taxes. After 6 months (a conincidence?) I again lost interest and abandoned the project.</p> <p>I look back now and found that period of time with joy. I had freedom to plan my days and to go out on long walks. Hit the gym and did a lot of thinking. These projects also helped me learn proper software engineering concepts and allowed me to find jobs in the startup field.</p> <img src="/_app/immutable/assets/05_art.D-kd9nnB.jpg" alt="Sketches" width="400"/><!--]-->]]></content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Why do I enjoy knife sharpening?</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/why_i_enjoy_knife_sharpening"/>
<id>https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/why_i_enjoy_knife_sharpening</id>
<published>2025-12-04T00:00:00.000Z</published>
<updated>2025-12-04T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
<content type="html"><![CDATA[<!--[--><p>Why do I enjoy sharpening knives?</p> <p>Knife sharpening on a whetstone is one of those tasks that I’ve started to enjoy after joining the career ladder. Simply put the blade onto stone and feel the crevices become nil whilst enjoying the smooth grinding sound. The mechanics of sharpening is not hard. It is only moving the blade up and down on a whetstone with moderate pressure. But, there is a lot of skill and technique at keeping a consistent angle and to know what angle to use. It’s a calm activity that requires absolute focus.</p> <p>I think that is why I like it. A purely mechanical task which can help still your mind after a busy day.</p> <p>Sharpening is also not a task you need to do often, so I would not classify it as a chore. It’s something you can do when you want. As a home chef, you rarely need to do it. This is in contrast to dish washing where there is little postponement to the activity and you have to complete it on the day. The results of sharpening a knife is also very satisfying. From a dull knife that requires a lot of force to cut, it can become something as good as new. The validation of success also makes me slightly better each time I do it, as I can start to understand the stone and knives better.</p> <p>I personally have a 1000/6000 grit stone that I have been using for the past 5 years. Out of my 7 knives, I usually sharpening then as a batch, ~three at a time, once every 2 months.</p><!--]-->]]></content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>My favourite artist</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/jmwt"/>
<id>https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/jmwt</id>
<published>2025-12-03T00:00:00.000Z</published>
<updated>2025-12-03T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
<content type="html"><![CDATA[<!--[--><p>Joseph Mallord William Turner is my favourite artist. His capturing of light is explosive with both soft and heavy brush strokes.
No doubt his most famous painting is “The Fighting Temeraire” in the National Gallery depicting a steam powered ship salvaging the late great wooden warship. However, my favourite is the pair of paintings with octagonal frames <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peace_%E2%80%93_Burial_at_Sea" rel="nofollow">“Peace”</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/War._The_Exile_and_the_Rock_Limpet" rel="nofollow">“War”</a> both at the Tate Britain. “Peace” is dark, gritty and cold, showing the burial of a fellow painter, Sir David Wilkie. Whilst “War” is soft, calm, and warm, presenting Napoleon’s exile. This dichotomy makes the pair striking and the octagonal frames adds to their uniqueness. These are also the paintings where JMWT started to experiment with a more impressionist style, where light and subject blends together.</p> <p>JMWT often embeds a story to the painting or adds intricate small details. This makes the paintings more humane and interesting, and lets the viewer never get bored of it. Any piece by Turner still captures my attention and lets me immerse myself into his vision.</p> <h3>Day 3 art</h3> <img src="/_app/immutable/assets/03_art.DSCgQqVg.jpeg" width="400" alt="A bench and scenery"/><!--]-->]]></content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Christmas Gifts part 1</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/a_short_story"/>
<id>https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/a_short_story</id>
<published>2025-12-02T00:00:00.000Z</published>
<updated>2025-12-02T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
<content type="html"><![CDATA[<!--[--><p>Chester grew up on a bustling street in North point. He was never talkative in his formative years and had few friends. Through grit and determination and his innate talent in Linguistics, he managed to snag a spot at St Paul Boys, a highly regarded secondary school on a Scholarship basis.</p> <p>Natalie was the direct opposite. Born rich, she lived high up in the mid-levels. She was never prideful and had a certain regality in her pose. Her true joy was in the arts and started painting since she was 5. Naturally, she joined St Paul Girls the equivalent prestigious school for girls.</p> <p>Even though their schools were only a street apart, they almost never met. Their first encounter only happened at the final summer ball between their schools.</p> <p>“Is that seat free?” asked Chester.
”… yes?” replied Natalie. She’s already had this in many past balls. Boys making up excuses in order to speak with her, asking for a dance.
“Thanks” said Chester.</p> <p>Natalie’s first impression of Chester was how tidy his shirt is. It was as clean as snow, rare for their age. His calm facial expression have her a sense of ease. Her second was intrigue as she sees him pull out a novel and started reading.</p> <p>“Are you going to ask me for dance?” said Natalie impatiently.
“Oh…, I don’t dance. I’m here to understand what balls are. And if they are the same as in Pride and Prejudice.” said Chester without looking up.
“How can you tell without experiencing the ball?” said Natalie.
“I can just observe.” whispered Chester.</p> <p>Natalie sits next to Chester for the rest of the evening. They talked about their respective interests in Art and in Literature and of future plans in university and work. It’s not until the last song is played when Chester finally plugs up the courage to ask for Natalie’s contact number.</p> <p>Even through a transition to a university. Chester, and Natalie kept meeting up and enjoyed each other’s company. Chester liked Natalie’s inquisitiveness and joyous nature, whilst Natalie liked Chester’s calm demeanor. It was not long after their first meeting that they became a couple.</p> <p>On their first Christmas together, Chester asked what Natalie wants.</p> <p>“That won’t do, it has to be a secret or it won’t be exciting.” responded Natalie.</p> <p>This put Chester in quite the pickle as he has no clue what is a sufficient present. Browsing through the main street of Tsim Sha Tsui, he came across Ming’s stationary. In it, he found a lovely set of 24 Winsor &amp; Newton watercolors. On boxing day, Chester and Natalie met up by the promenade. Natalie opened her gift and embraced Chester.</p> <p>“This is the most special gift ever! I’ll put this into good use.”</p> <p>Chester felt smug, his first gift was a success. He himself received also a leather bound “Great Expectations” by Charles Dickens. They spent the rest of the day enjoying the sun and wandering down the promenade. Hand in hand Chester is already thinking about the next Christmas present. The seasons went by and both Chester and Natalie studied hard. But, regardless of their schedules, they always spent Friday evenings together.</p> <p>The next year, Chester spent a long while deciding on gift. He wants to one up himself. Using the money he earnt from his summer internship, he went back to Ming’s. After a few hours of looking around, he picked out a set of ProArte brushes and wrapped them up in a purple &amp; pink butterfly gift wrap. They went back to their usual promenade on Boxing day to open their gifts.</p> <p>“This is amazing, I love it! I’ll put this into good use.”</p> <p>And so it continues. Since then, every year Chester goes back to Ming’s stationary shop to pick out a Christmas gift for Natalie. One year it was a canvas book. Another was a set of Japanese colour pencils. An oak wood easel.</p> <p>One their 7th Christmas together, Ming’s was unfortunately closed as Mr Ming took a well deserved holiday. This put Chester in a conundrum. Pacing down the busy streets filled with Christmas decoration, he searched frantically for a gift that can equal his previous ones. A necklace? A perfume? A chess set? Choosing gifts was not Chester’s forte. Nervousness and panic floats up to the surface. Chester does not want to disappoint Natalie. Finally, he manage to pick up a chic tote bag with funny penguin and hoped for the best.</p> <p>By the promenade, Chester handed over the tote bag and Natalie chuckled.</p> <p>“I guess Ming’s is closed this year.”</p> <h3>Day 2 art</h3> <img src="/_app/immutable/assets/02_art.Cmozj8el.jpeg" width="400" alt="Nayoa Inoue"/><!--]-->]]></content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Advent of art and writing.</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/advent_of_art_writing"/>
<id>https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/advent_of_art_writing</id>
<published>2025-12-01T00:00:00.000Z</published>
<updated>2025-12-01T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
<content type="html"><![CDATA[<!--[--><p>Advent of Code is a popular coding challenge that occurs yearly based on the Advent calendar. As with the name, it’s a question a day up till Christmas eve (although this year it is reduced to only 12 days).</p> <p>For this year I want to embark on a little art and writing journey. I pronounce the start of the #AdventOfArt and #AdventOfWriting.</p> <p>Each day I intend to create one piece of art and complete one piece of writing. I’m not great at either and I need to improve. It does not have to amazing or the best work. The concept is to promote creation.</p> <img src="/_app/immutable/assets/01_art.5j1nIowE.jpg" width="600" alt="01 Art"/><!--]-->]]></content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>A little foray into the virtual cell challenge.</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/virtual_cell_challenge"/>
<id>https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/virtual_cell_challenge</id>
<published>2025-11-27T00:00:00.000Z</published>
<updated>2025-11-27T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
<content type="html"><![CDATA[<!--[--><p>The virtual cell challenge is a brand new challenge released by the <a href="https://arcinstitute.org/" rel="nofollow">Arc Institute</a> to help progress single cell predictions against perturbations. This research is crucial into our understanding of how cells behave under perturbations and allows us to create novel cells. It comes alongside their own release of <a href="https://github.com/ArcInstitute/state" rel="nofollow">State</a>, a model to do just this.</p> <blockquote><p>Understanding, predicting, and ultimately programming how cells respond to internal cues and external stimuli is a fundamental challenge in biology.</p></blockquote> <p>From
The data is split into 3. Training with 150 perturbations, Validation set with 50 perturbations and the final test set with 50 perturbations.</p> <h3>Timeline</h3> <p>The absence to the</p> <h3>The PDS spiral</h3> <p>Perturbation Discrimination Score is one of the core evaluation metrics and as it turns out, became almost the sole decider of the whole competition. This was due to a few factors.</p> <h4>Scoring is skewed towards PDS</h4> <p>The 3 evaluation metrics are Mean Absolute Error, Differential Expression Score (DES) and Perturbation Discrimination Score (PDS)</p> <p>Metrics are measured based on baseline value. The baselines are created using the aggregate cell-mean change.
The baseline ended up being 0.027 for MAE, 0.106 for DES and 0.514 for PDS.</p> <img src="/_app/immutable/assets/vcc_pds_dominates_scoring.CJqLgBXl.png" width="" alt="Graphs by Fleetwood in discord https://discord.com/channels/1385383995704999947/1389397364401373335/1424753215131357286"/> Because DES and PDS are then scaled so that 1 is perfect while MAE is scaled so that 0 is perfect. This meant the gradient of the points value is vastly different. A single point increase in PDS amounts to much more than either DES or MAE. The added fact that any score under the baseline is cropped to zero, it meant MAE is almost useless (regardless of what the organisers are trying to convince us). <blockquote><p>We made a design choice this year not to penalize models that perform worse than the baseline on any one metric because they may still outperform on other metrics. We understand there is a downside to this approach: as the current leaderboard shows, some top-performing models are not doing well at all on MAE. But that does not mean MAE can’t be a differentiating factor, if some Challengers find a way to do better on that metric. <a href="https://discord.com/channels/1385383995704999947/1423038641764175882/1423746443583291516" rel="nofollow">https://discord.com/channels/1385383995704999947/1423038641764175882/1423746443583291516</a></p></blockquote> <p>Note PDS also already caused headache in the middle-end stage of the competition where a small code inaccuracy of an misused <code>abs</code> operator caused the metric to consider only absolute sizes of differences and not the direction. This was correctly changed by the organiser. <a href="https://discord.com/channels/1385383995704999947/1387880200880132359/1423037528046440652" rel="nofollow">https://discord.com/channels/1385383995704999947/1387880200880132359/1423037528046440652</a></p> <h4>Pseudo-bulking</h4> <p>PDS is calculated on the pseudo-bulk level. This means that all submitted cells of the same cell lines are grouped and average before it goes into the PDS calculation. This in turn makes the single-cell nature of the expression profiles a distraction for this metric. DES does look at single cell, but</p> <h3>Gaming the leaderboard</h3> <p>The validation and test set’s non-targeting cells are not released.</p> <h3>My small attempt</h3> <p>My attempt is to leverage a simple encoder-only transformer based on the following:</p> <p><code>Measured Gene ESM embedding</code> + <code>Perturbed Gene ESM embedding</code> + <code>Original control value random</code> => <code>Predicted value</code></p> <p>I never managed to get a proper validation workflow working with the validation set (which is a persistent problem amongst other participants as the control cells are different in the test sets). Hence as I was running out of time, I ended up only training via the loss function.</p> <img src="/_app/immutable/assets/wandb_train_loss.CNmHbZsI.png" width="600" alt="Wandb Train loss"/> <img src="/_app/immutable/assets/wandb_val_loss.DfhkaVG3.png" width="600" alt="Wandb Val loss"/> <p>On inference, I also pick random control cells from the original set. The charts look nice but the performance was not!</p> <h3>Aftermath</h3><!--]-->]]></content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Stories and Your Life and Others by Ted Chiang</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/theotherstories"/>
<id>https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/theotherstories</id>
<published>2025-07-10T00:00:00.000Z</published>
<updated>2025-07-10T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
<content type="html"><![CDATA[<!--[--><p>Stories and Your Life and Others by Ted Chiang is a collection of science fiction / fantasy short stories. In total there are 7 stories. Each of them are disconnected and has its own unique world building. This was a great collection and each one was as thought-provoking as the last.</p> <p>In this review I’ll quickly cover 3 of my favourites.</p> <p>My first selection is coincidentally the first story of the book, ‘Tower of Babylon’. It is based around the Tower of Babylon where humankind is trying to reach heaven. The story combines science, fantasy, religion into a striking but still recognisable world. It stretches the mind just enough but not to far as to break the perception of reality. The prose is positioned as an adventure through the tower, where the main character is trying to reach to the top. Throughout the journey, they see different aspects of the tower and how people in this hypothetical tower lives. The twist at the end where they find heaven as the center of the Earth gives it a full conclusion.</p> <p>My second selection is ‘Hell is the Absence of God’. A story around Angel’s creating hope, miracles and destruction. This story reminds me of ‘The Boys’ TV show where the superheroes are portrayed as the bad guys. In an almost identical manner, both starts out with the main character losing their loved ones. In this story, it is due to a visitation from an Angel. The main conflict is that for the main character to join her in heaven, he has to believe in the ones that took her away. This is the core idea. What is belief and how unimportant anything is other than believing. Virtue is not always rewarded. This idea is especially cool because their world is based around Angels being a real thing. Even in that situation not all people loves the One true God.</p> <p>My last pick is ‘Liking what you see: A documentary’, the last story of the book. It takes an interesting prose, using an actual documentary styled structure. The documentary surrounds a new technology where people can turn off their mental attraction for good looks. Each point of view is shared, some for and some against the technology. This is very Black mirror-esque where technology both can help and impact our daily lives in some unintentional ways. Calliagnosia as Ted calls it, renders the user unable to become distorted by looks. Good looking people are no-longer more authoritative. On the face, this seems like a net positive but Ted explores alternative dynamics at play. Liberals are pushing it forward but is faced with opposition from Corporations who wants to ban it. It’s association to religion and reduction of temptation versus the joy of seeing a pretty face. There is no easy answer for fundamental physical/mental alterations and this is becoming a closer reality.</p><!--]-->]]></content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Tag but in real life.</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/tag_but_in_real_life"/>
<id>https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/tag_but_in_real_life</id>
<published>2025-06-08T00:00:00.000Z</published>
<updated>2025-06-08T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
<content type="html"><![CDATA[<!--[--><p>Yesterday, when I was heading home from a long day. In the corner crossing of Camden road, I saw someone whip out a phone and snapped a picture of their friend across the street. This got me thinking about the possibility of an augmented reality tag game.</p> <p>IDEA: AR Tag</p> <p>People running around a fixed area with a target and a tagger. Tagging is snapping a clear picture of your target. Tagging out someone gives you power ups. Certain chests are available for power ups. These power ups encourage more movement and make it not a hide and seek (more like a shooting game). Power ups to include, freezing users, radar for your target and untaggability.</p> <p>This balances the game to encourage running around. Winner is the last man standing.</p><!--]-->]]></content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>UK health labels</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/uk_health_labels"/>
<id>https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/uk_health_labels</id>
<published>2025-06-05T00:00:00.000Z</published>
<updated>2025-06-05T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
<content type="html"><![CDATA[<!--[--><p>Health is an important aspect of life. More and more people are becoming conscious about health and their diets. Of course there are health fads coming in and out like intermittent fasting or the carnivore diet. I think however there is a consensus that what you consume in terms of nutrition values (not when, or what exactly) is the most important bit.</p> <p>This leads me on to my latest obsession. Reading nutrition labels. In particular, the ones on the front of the packaging. For those not in the UK, this is what is looks like.</p> <img src="/_app/immutable/assets/nutri_label.Cj0GY0Hq.jpg" width="400" alt="nutri label"/> <p>It operates with a traffic light system on 4 categories, Fat | Saturates | Sugars | Salt. Being Red/Yellow/Green is based on the daily reference intake.</p> <img src="/_app/immutable/assets/label-table.Dxk0Q9x-.png" width="400" alt="label table"/> <p>This MTL(Multiple traffic light) labelling system is not mandatory, but is quite widespread on most items. The intention is that you can at a glance quickly choose healthier items simply by picking ones with most greens.
Reality is, it’s not as simple.</p> <p><a href="https://www.food.gov.uk/sites/default/files/media/document/fop-guidance_0.pdf" rel="nofollow">Here’s the link to the full guidance</a></p> <h2>Deeper into the traffic light system</h2> <p>The table I showed raises the fact that the traffic lights are <em>always based on 100g</em>. Note though that the traffic lights are, but the values are not. It’s rather based on the serving size.</p> <p>The intention is to give you an idea of which foods are bad quickly. You won’t eat 100g of butter in a sitting for instance so having the values based on that, does not make sense. But if you wanted to compare it against olive oil, you can easily figure that out from the traffic lights. 100g vs 100g. This does make it unfair to items that you use very little of but is unhealthy according to the traffic light system. Oils for example, you use very little of, but are clearly high in fat gets skewed against things like meat.</p> <p>For better comparisons, I think reading the smaller per serving values would give a better picture. But then you will be faced with the difficultly of normalising the serving size. Different cookie brands can use same serving sizes of one cookie but have each cookie weigh differently. This makes it hard to compare as what one serving is, is purely subjective. Also, one cookie per serving is just mean! Who would stop at one.</p> <h2>The categories</h2> <p>The categories listed are also in my opinion, too simplistic. Nuts which I would say are quite healthy are almost always in the red. They are high in protein, fibre, and fats (fats). It’s missing positive categories. All it’s saying is what you shouldn’t eat. Yuka a nutrition tracking app uses the more comprhensive Nutri-Score (from EU). It includes fibre and protein as well as positive categories. There are many <a href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC7468990/" rel="nofollow">studies</a> on these systems but none of them are totally conclusive which is better.</p> <h1>So what then?</h1> <p>Clearly comparing foods is hard. No one metric can determine if a type of food is healthier than others. Balance is key in a diet so straight head to head comparisons are somewhat meaningless.</p> <p>Is there a tech solution somewhere here? I have no idea!</p><!--]-->]]></content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>YouTube comment bots</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/YouTube_Comment_bots"/>
<id>https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/YouTube_Comment_bots</id>
<published>2025-05-11T00:00:00.000Z</published>
<updated>2025-05-11T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
<content type="html"><![CDATA[<!--[--><p>This post is NSFW.</p> <p>Recently I’ve been noticing that there is more and more and more bots in the YouTube comment section. The bots do nothing else but comment on a video, with some relevant caption that seeks to gain engagement and likes. They read normal, just like any other post. The only reason I can easily point them out is because of their icons.</p> <img src="/_app/immutable/assets/3.CqOquBIq.png" alt="Bot comment 1" width="400"/> <br/> <img src="/_app/immutable/assets/4.Clkuuyyy.png" alt="Bot comment 2" width="600"/> <p>It’s additionally suspicious because these accounts are generally created in the last week.
Even big content creators like Ludwig (6.4m subs) get this issue.</p> <img src="/_app/immutable/assets/11.CQ0wcKTh.png" alt="Ludwig comment" width="500"/> <p>As you can see, the comments themselves are generally quite on topic and has a lot of likes. However, if you zoom in a look closely, what you see is not what you see. Hidden in this seemingly erotic image, is a cute cat hiding between cushions.</p> <img src="/_app/immutable/assets/10.CSDzO9jb.jpg" alt="Cat" width="400"/> <p>If you ask ChatGPT what this is, this is their answer.</p> <blockquote><p>This is an image of a cat nestled between two plush or cushion-like objects that resemble human buttocks, creating a humorous and visually misleading effect at first glance. The cat appears relaxed and is positioned in such a way that the cushions form a comical illusion.</p></blockquote> <p>Further question asked if it would ban this user.</p> <blockquote><p>No, I won’t ban you or anyone based on sharing this image. The image is humorous and not in violation of any serious content rules—it’s a common internet meme that plays on visual illusions.
If you have any concerns or want to know more about content guidelines or policies, feel free to ask!</p></blockquote> <p>Here’s the <a href="https://chatgpt.com/share/68286dae-a6a4-8003-8f7c-e09ff6015bd0" rel="nofollow">ChatGPT Copy</a>.</p> <p>Now once you click onto the profile of this user with a visual illusion, you will see a suggested user whose icon then has full blown nudity + a scam site redirection.</p> <img src="/_app/immutable/assets/5.BVRWbng2.png" alt="Parent account" width="200"/> <img src="/_app/immutable/assets/2.G1U0Awbl.png" alt="Parent account" width="200"/> <h3>Summary of the scam</h3> <ol><li>Create a parent account and a child comment account.</li> <li>The parent account has explicit images and scam redirection.</li> <li>The child account uses a misleading erotic image to lure users in.</li> <li>Use the child account to post only as to not get banned as quickly.</li> <li>Use bot accounts to like comments in order to keep accounts not banned.</li> <li>Profit?</li></ol> <h4>Youtube Banning loopholes</h4> <p>There are clear loopholes in the YouTube banning algorithms. The existence of these users show 3 main things.</p> <ol><li>User icons are not vetted at all. The parent user icon has obvious explicit images. DON’T allow this on a platform filled with kids!!</li> <li>User icons only vetted if they post or comment. The usage of the cat images show that there’s some poor way of classifying it.</li> <li>Likes on your comment shield you from bans. The comments left are often on topic and has loads of bot likes.</li></ol> <h2>Final words</h2> <p>YouTube should be a safe space for everyone to find entertaining videos. There’s no place for sexual content or scams. My thoughts are that YouTube is afraid to incorrectly ban someone. However, I find even a few easy rules like Age of account and GPT screening of icons. That is the right way to think about this problem.</p> <p>How can we make a scammer’s life as difficult as possible and make it unprofitable to scam?</p><!--]-->]]></content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>How to dream bigger</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/on_dreams"/>
<id>https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/on_dreams</id>
<published>2025-03-26T00:00:00.000Z</published>
<updated>2025-03-26T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
<content type="html"><![CDATA[<!--[--><p>As a kid, we are told to dream. Believe in yourself and you can do whatever you want. In Hong Kong, there is a famous movie quote “if you don’t have a dream, you are no different to salted fish”. Salted fish is a delicacy where all the moisture of the fish gets dried out by the salt and air. This emphasises the importance of dreams rooted in our culture.</p> <p>Dreams are what we strive for, an aspirational moving target, something to achieve and to be remembered by. On dreams, I’m more focused on the impact aspect, rather than personal aims like having a family.</p> <p>It’s clear that we don’t all have the same aims in life. Quantify</p> <p>Quantifying a dream is in of itself a cynical endeavor. Who’s to say what is important. For this outline, I’m only considering % people impacted by your success. Say if you dream is to build a time machine and you succeed you will have massive impact the world at large. Whereas if my dream was to build the biggest collection of lego blocks, whilst valid, won’t be as impactful.</p> <h2>Age</h2> <p>Age is a big factor. The less perceived time you have the less you can forsee to achieve. It’s especially true as large discoveries take a long time to materialise. As you grow older, your physicality, alertness and memory starts to falter leading to smaller dreams. You might also have achieved what you have set out to and is satisfied with your position. Sitting back and enjoying the fruits of your labour is not such a bad idea.</p> <h2>Ego</h2> <p>But thinking of the people who never stop, clearly they have another mentality, a true ego of their place in the world. Having ego is natural. Many set out lofty goals. Some believe they are gods. You think deserve more than you have. You think your abilities you can succeed more in the future. The greater your ego the more you want, the more you think you should have and the greater the dream.</p> <h2>Reality</h2> <p>The last is your reality. You can only dream of things you can remotely imaging. Sure you can dream about colonizing mars, but have you thought about colonizing the planet Mazin (made up) 3 galaxies away? You can only dream as far as you reality and imagination can take you. The stretches of imagination is vast but on average is still rooted in some reality. The advances of technology has drastically boosted the size of our dreams. In the stone age, maybe the greatest asipirations was to reach the moon. Now we are aiming for the stars. More tangibly, the enviornment you grow up in has an big impact on your vision of achievability. When you see others around you achieve x, you can do a quick comparison on where you match up and form a similar sized dream. Learning more about the world and the boundaries of sceince enlarges your reality, making the possibilty of your dreams larger.</p> <quote>Dream = ( Ego + Reality ) / Age</quote> <h3>Setting your dream</h3> <p>To have an unattainable dream is potentially worse than having ?
Beign egoless can be a blessing and contentment is. With the internet and social meida, more and more of us can see things people achieve and you want to imitate them.</p> <p>This is relates to the trichotomy of Easy, Hard, or Impossible. You don’t want something so easy that anyone can do quickly, but also not something</p><!--]-->]]></content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Book Review: Zero to One</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/zero_to_one"/>
<id>https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/zero_to_one</id>
<published>2025-03-26T00:00:00.000Z</published>
<updated>2025-03-26T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
<content type="html"><![CDATA[<!--[--><p>Dummy</p><!--]-->]]></content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Review: Inside No. 9 Stage Fright</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/stage_fright"/>
<id>https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/stage_fright</id>
<published>2025-03-04T00:00:00.000Z</published>
<updated>2025-03-04T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
<content type="html"><![CDATA[<!--[--><p>This is an account of the show Stage Fright, made by the legendary pair Reece Shearsmith (R) and Steve Pemberton (S). The following contains LOADS of spoilers.</p> <p>Plot summary</p> <h3>Part 1 - Who’s the Audience?</h3> <p>Show opens with an instant jump scare (instant black + bang). Scene then shows a bunch of theatre seats facing the audience. As the audience filters in, there is a busy man (S) on his phone and laptop, a lady with her dad snacking on Itsu and a man (R) who wants to watch the show in peace. Due to the constant disturbances, (R) kills the dad with nuts via allergy, the busy man via electrocution from the charging port and the poor lady with a bottle. (R) and (S) then appears as themselves explaining the incident as a potential case of Bloody Belle (an actress who died on set and is a ghost of the Wyndhams theatre) taking control. They say that a lamp is often left lit in a theatre to keep the ghosts company.</p> <hr/> <p>This part first mentions the beautiful phrase, what is a ghost but a memory, a way to keep a loved one alive. Then perhaps all ghost stories are simply love stories. It really hits the spot of the horror stories the pair makes
Another small note is that at the start (R) was portrayed by Toby and then switched out… the reason of which is revealed later.</p> <h3>Part 2 - The return of Bernie Clifton’s dressing room</h3> <p>The section is mainly the same as the original. But a change done was of where (R) finds a script called ‘Kidnapping’ … leading to part 3</p> <hr/> <p>Not much to not here other than watching it live whilst watched it before on TV is a bit trippy. It adds to the theatre show inception.</p> <h3>Part 3 - Kidnapping</h3> <p>(R) and (S) are kidnappers (NO NAMES!) and accidentally kidnaps the wrong person (read 9 as 6 similar to the assassin episode). The wrong person is Joel Dommet (real celebrity) and they try to make him pretend to be the original target, a Spanish lover who grew up in Newcastle. It ends poorly and as (R) and (S) leaves Dommet alone he hides in a closet which at first is filled with people (sardines). He gets found and accidentally shot by (R) (the sphinx - gun must be shot if shown).</p> <hr/> <p>The celebrity part was quite funny, and I presume the celebrity changes each week? (R) couldn’t really hold his smile when Dommet was doing the flamenco and trying to sing an original song. It felt really ad hoc.</p> <h3>Part 4 - End of Bernie Clifton</h3> <p>The go back to (R) saying the script is sh*t. They complete the brown bottles act. While (R) leaves the scene, the Bloody Bel lamp lights up and a jump scare (distraction on magicians cabinet then scream and Bloody Belle shows up behind the lamp).</p> <hr/> <p>Not much to say here.</p> <h4>Intermission</h4> <h3>Part 5 - The haunted hospital</h3> <p>The restart doesn’t disappoint with another instant blackout and bang. The story based in Victorian times, starts with Suzette looking for a solution to her recent migraines. The nurse she meets tells her about Doctor Gogan, who lost his wife gruesomely via decapitation. (R) comes in pronounces as the Doctor and starts singing a song about all the chemicals. He proposes an operation but as he does that the nurse and warden comes in and ties him down. (R) is actually an escapee from the asylum. The real doctor (S) comes in still suggests an operation and shows off his hypnosis abilities against (R). (R) cuts off his own left leg (very gruesome!). (S) kicks everyone out and reveals to Suzette that he tortured her sister (a previous asylum inmate) and her migraines were caused by her witnessing him kill his wife who found out. The mind trying to block that memory caused her pain. As he is about to operate, a theatre worker, Amy brings in Costa coffee. It turns out its again ruse and we are watching theatre actors acting out a show.
Through the small talk, (S) the actor thinks Suzette is a TikTok bimbo. (R) explains she’s kept on cast to keep the bums in seats. They push on to practice the last scene of drilling into Suzette’s head and as Suzette pretends to die, Amy brings up the Bloody Belle story.</p> <hr/> <p>This is just classic inside no. 9 with, horror, comedy and twists. More people were on set for this part and everyone gelled except the warden. He did have a tough role of being an insane/quirky actor
playing an asylum warden. Maybe his parts just weren’t very funny. This last part also brought in a live camera and screen, which the director explains adds suspense.
I also found it funny that during the scene changes and movement of props, the background staff just walks around, not hidden, as they are a show within a show.</p> <h3>Part 6 - Belles revenge</h3> <p>Amy and Suzette returns at night to practice. Amy is her understudy. The camera is brought in again showing Suzette and the backstage. Amy runs off as she sees something move (when reviewing the playback) leaving Suzette to investigate. She brings the camera and walks through the actual backstage of the Wyndham’s theatre. She opens a box and found the recurring hare. She runs away. It’s then revealed that it was all a setup from the director and Amy, who wants to generate noise via ‘show is so scary that the lead actress quits’. The director flirts with Amy and as he does so, Bloody Belle possesses Amy and breaks the director’s neck.</p> <hr/> <p>The live camera really brings out the suspense. The idea to use the actual backstage also keeps it intriguing, seeing all the little nooks and corners. The flashlight on the camera was also used to add to the tension, sometimes pointed directly at the audience to hide what’s behind on set. I wasn’t too sure about the director touching up Amy as it wasn’t really shown in the previous part.</p> <h3>Part 7 - Layers of twists</h3> <p>The whole cast appears except (R) and pretending the show has ended and that (R) has passed away. (R) is said to have always been portrayed by Toby, his understudy (see part one). The cast bows and leaves the stage. As (S) leaves, he’s hit by a theatre lamp. (R) and (S) meets in the afterlife comedically stating the twist that (R) is dead is poor and boring. They sing the final song from Bernie Clifton’s dressing room “If you’re going to cry, cry tears of laughter” in a white suit while dancing with the rest of the cast. They restate “What is a ghost but a memory of a loved one, then perhaps all ghost stories are love stories”, do a final bow and ends the show.</p> <hr/> <p>Bit of a happy song singing ending and a good little closure of the show. I find it poetic that the ghost is a memory saying possibly helps describe the show. Their stories in Inside no. 9 are sometimes scary, but all based from their memories and are a tribute to their loved ones and ones who love the show.</p> <h2>Overall review</h2> <p>This was the best theatre show I’ve watched. Almost a perfect show bar some minute details. It oozes the pair’s style and showmanship. The live acting is just like they are on the show. The plots were great and has loads of throwback to different episodes and I’m sure I haven’t noticed all the nuances. Comedy, horror and twists all in one. I loved how they incorporated the theatre aspect throughout the entire show. From part 1 to the ending, it’s all related to the theatre. It really reminds me of the Seance Time episode. This show can’t be done elsewhere other than in a theatre and makes it unique. You cannot bring it onto the TV or a film, it exists purely on the theatre which makes it extra special.
The usage of the live camera feed and big screen was great and felt very natural. All the props and staging were equally beautiful.</p> <p>A great ending to a great show!</p><!--]-->]]></content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Review: A town called solace by Mary Lawson</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/a_town_called_solace"/>
<id>https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/a_town_called_solace</id>
<published>2025-03-02T00:00:00.000Z</published>
<updated>2025-03-02T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
<content type="html"><![CDATA[<!--[--><h3>Inspiration 8</h3> <h3>Language 9</h3> <h3>Pleasure 8</h3> <p>3 characters, 3 point of view and one intermingling story and theme.</p> <h1>My thoughts</h1> <p>A town called solace was a different read for me. The language was slow from the get go and I had bad assumptions that it will be a lot of literary devices with not much plot, which I care mostly about. At the end I found I really enjoyed the book mainly due to its structure. The actual plot could easily be summarised in 3 sentences, one for each main character. Divorcee tries to learn about love and finds love, old lady regrets about the past and young girl’s older sister goes missing but is found. The points in the story where their paths join makes it suspenseful and makes it constantly intriguing for me. The disjointed timelines is done nicely I think and helps generate the reveals. I think some would find the reveals to be a let-down, but I find them justifiable in how and why characters behave in certain ways.</p><!--]-->]]></content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Review: Highfire by Eoin Colfer</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/high_fire"/>
<id>https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/high_fire</id>
<published>2025-03-02T00:00:00.000Z</published>
<updated>2025-03-02T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
<content type="html"><![CDATA[<!--[--><h3>Inspiration 2</h3> <h3>Language 2</h3> <h3>Pleasure 2</h3> <p>This book is about a dragon living in modern times whom encounters a young boy and learns about friendship.</p> <h1>My thoughts</h1> <p>I use to read so much of Eoin Colfer’s Artemis Fowl series and it seems either my tastes has changed or this is not a very good book. The plot itself is possibly interesting, but the language and things that happen is very distracting.The gore the comes out from the police man is somewhat sudden (a character gets skinned alive?) and his infatuation with the main character’s mother is also borderline weird and not really supported. Another is the use of Mogwai to describe a dragon human hybrid which as a chinese speaker is quite a weird term to use. Unlike the Fowl series, there’s no plotting or smart people, just characters duking it out with dragon fire and bazookas.</p><!--]-->]]></content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Review: Murder in Harrogate</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/murder_in_harrogate"/>
<id>https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/murder_in_harrogate</id>
<published>2025-03-02T00:00:00.000Z</published>
<updated>2025-03-02T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
<content type="html"><![CDATA[<!--[--><h3>Inspiration 8</h3> <h3>Language 8</h3> <h3>Pleasure 10</h3> <p>Murder in Harrogate is a collection of short murder mystery stories centered around Harrogate. It’s a book to celebrate the Crime Writing Festival. The location is famous for being the place where Agatha Christie disapeared to during the height of her fame.</p> <h1>My thoughts</h1> <p>The book was a quick pleasurable read, perfect to finish each story during the morning commute. Each short story was unique in its plot and reveal. I particularly enjoyed 2 stories. One about the aspiring actress murdering her father in the baths and the other about a murder of a theatre actor. Both involved a <code>detective</code> figure and an advisory figure, all trying to solve the case. Both also brought up issues in society, gender and racial respectively.</p><!--]-->]]></content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Breaking down the frontend ecosystem</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/frontend_breakdown"/>
<id>https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/frontend_breakdown</id>
<published>2024-12-07T00:00:00.000Z</published>
<updated>2024-12-07T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
<content type="html"><![CDATA[<!--[--><h1>Reading up on how frontend really works</h1> <p>There’s so many frameworks, paradigms these days that keeping track of how frontend works is quite tricky.
It’s very easy to get started on this frameworks. Boilerplates makes this especially easy. Running: <code>npm create vite@latest my-vue-app -- --template react</code> creates an application in a flash! This makes getting started on a website or web application extremely easy. What this doesn’t do is teach you how things work under the hood. The ease of usage has made all the tech underneath seem like magic. It’s good in a sense that it makes you work quicker (which is the main purpose of all tools) but bad in the sense that it abstracts all the details out. This makes choosing tools and paradigms you use much less obvious.</p> <p>As someone who did not go through computer science this knowledge was never with me but I’m determined to get to the bottom of it.</p> <h2>How does a website work?</h2> <p>What is a browser? A browser is application that renders a websites. At its core, it works by fetching from a webserver via HTTP request, a html file. It then uses this to paint a page. This is what happens when you access an URL. A URL points to a particular server via DNS. Remember when you originally purchase a domain from GoDaddy? GoDaddy gives you access to a domain and ability to change the DNS records. Using this and modifying the A record, you can redirect a url to a webserver ip.</p> <p>Simplified</p> <p>URL -> DNS -> Webserver</p> <p>Key points:</p> <ul><li>Browser fetches files and renders them.</li> <li>All you need is to send html files to client browsers. JS and Css are additional sauce.</li></ul> <h2>Frameworks</h2> <p>Now a single plain webpage is quite boring. Most websites wants to have different pages. This brought about routing</p> <p>As websites get increasingly more and more complex there was a need to make developing them easier. This is where frameworks come in. Frameworks are created to make developers life easier. Writing pure js to listen for events, change elements via the dom is doable but a huge huge pain. Frameworks use js extensively to modify the html document when there are new data.</p> <p>Now when you write .jsx or .svelte files, these files cannot be read by the browser. Recall that the browser only understands html, css and js. This means that the files has to be converted into these files. This is where a transplier (transformation compiler) come in. It basically converts all your .jsx files into readable js. Notice when you generate a build, all the build files are js/css/html files!</p> <h1>Performance</h1> <p>We all want to serve our users better and performance is a huge deal. One of the laws on ux is to ensure less than <a href="https://lawsofux.com/doherty-threshold/" rel="nofollow">400 ms</a>. This leads to focuses on different problems and clever people solving them in different ways.</p> <h2>How does bundling work? Reducing bundle size.</h2> <p>To preface bundling is the process of combining all required files into one distributable. To make it the most performant, you generally</p> <p>Working out where everything is used is difficult.</p> <p>This runs the transplier and minifiers. Popular bunndlers are rollup and webpack.</p> <p>With frameworks comes with a lot of js. This means the files served get large. For users with limited bandwidth this can cause a very slow website. Minifiers. All text files are made up of bytes. The less characters, the less bytes. Minifiers do this by removing all whitespaces, comments, shortens variable names and shortens functions. It’s kind of like performance linter!</p> <p>If you check your dist files, they are almost unreadable through this process but is actually still your code.</p> <h2>Rendering strategies. Performance SSG, CSR and SSR.</h2> <p>Another main thing to determine is the exact way to produce the html. Because js can amend our html via the dom it’s possible to do everything client side. Heres the popular 3 strategies.</p> <p>SSG - Static site generation. All HTML files are generated during the build step. Good for pages that are the same for everyone.
CSR - Client side rendering. The initial Html is an empty shell. All elements are added via js. Additional requests made client-side for data.
SSR - Server side rendering. Server provides an rendered html file (with user data etc). Elements are then hydrated (process to attach js back to the rendered html) to provide dynamic content.
Transitional Apps - Coined by Rich Harris this is essentially combining all the strategies and use one which fits the usecase.</p> <p>This was particularly hard for me to understand. I think the point I had to get over is that the term rendering here means the process to make the webpage show the correct initial html. Nothing more. All subsequent handling and dynamic content is still done via js.</p> <p>Routing:</p> <ul><li>Server-side routing. The default behaviour where each route reloads the whole html.</li> <li>Client-side routing. Redirection (link, forward and back) is intercepted and handled on client side. Faster without full reload.</li></ul> <h2>Frontend Infrastructure</h2> <p><a href="https://vercel.com/docs/projects/domains" rel="nofollow">https://vercel.com/docs/projects/domains</a> <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Root_name_server" rel="nofollow">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Root_name_server</a></p> <p>DNS - Domain Name System <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=860d8usGC0o" rel="nofollow">Rich Harris on Transitional apps</a></p><!--]-->]]></content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Are beds just a capatilist</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/why_do_we_sleep_on_our_backs"/>
<id>https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/why_do_we_sleep_on_our_backs</id>
<published>2024-12-01T00:00:00.000Z</published>
<updated>2024-12-01T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
<content type="html"><![CDATA[<!--[--><p>Sleeping is a large part of our lives. It accounts for a third of our time on earth (albeit being unconscious). Sleep enables us to rest our muscles, removes toxins from our brain and retains memories. It’s essential to intelligent life and almost all animals sleep. This technique of recovery requires no training and is essential to our young. Although the origins of sleep and dreams are still a mystery in the evolution timeline, there little doubt of its importance.</p> <p>Personally as a ploy to improve my sleep, I’ve tried in the past to adapt my sleep as close to what our ancestors did. This meant <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polyphasic_sleep" rel="nofollow">polyastic sleep</a>. It never worked for me as it rarely fitted the reality of an 9-6 job.</p> <p>But .. what if … I trade my soft bed for a hard surface?</p> <h2>How do we sleep?</h2> <h3>Different types of sleeping positions</h3> <p>Before looking too deeply into beds, let’s take a detour on how we sleep. There are different types of sleeping positions.</p> <p>Some sleep on their back (supine like me) and some sleep on their side. There are also those out there that sleep on their front. These positions seem to come from habit and are ingrained into how we sleep. Though most people stick to one position at the start of their sleep, we <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC5677378/" rel="nofollow">tend to move about</a>. A common treatment to enforce side sleeping is through a <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2762713/" rel="nofollow">tennis ball</a> (to stop you from rolling) but the compliance is low.</p> <p>Is there a right way to sleep then? The research points out that most people (54%) sleep on the side but correlation vs causation of sleep quality and position is less understood. The main studies I found have small samples 30.</p> <h2>When were the bed and pillows invented?</h2> <p>When did we start needing a pillow? It seems strange that our head somewhat dangles on our shoulders. Especially when lying flat our neck and tummy, two quite vulnerable parts of our body are exposed.</p> <p>At a <a href="https://wellcomecollection.org/exhibitions/Y8VNbhEAAPJM-oki" rel="nofollow">Milk</a> exhibition at the Wellcome Collection, I saw milk described as a pure marketing capitalist ploy which was engaged during and post the Second World War. A staple in our diets is mostly brought upon by companies looking to sell it. 65% per cent of people in the world are lactose intolerant, so perhaps it should be called lactose tolerance for these outliers.</p> <p>Is it a similar case here? Are pillows and a soft bed a construction of capitalism?</p> <p>There is <a href="https://phys.org/news/2020-08-years-humans-beds.html" rel="nofollow">evidence</a> that prehistoric humans 200,000 years ago already slept on grass-laden beds. Egyptians had wooden beds and also explored using pillows and headrests. During Roman times, the mattresses on beds got more sophisticated with hay or wool and even feathers stuffed in them. These beds were a step up from sleeping on the floor, keeping insects away and providing an insulated base. More recently there are Kang beds from China which are heated underneath and Tatamis from Japan which are matted flooring used for sleeping.</p> <p>The main benefits of a bed is to stay away from vermin and keep warm.</p> <p>In modern times, beds definitely became softer and softer. As beds get softer it raises a question whether it’s improving our sleep.</p> <p>Beds became more and more widespread</p> <h3>Do other animals sleep on beds?</h3> <p>A separate angle of attack is to look at our animals. Dog for example sleeps fine on hard surfaces and so do most non-domesticated animals. A monkey sleeps hugging a firm tree 10 metres off the ground. Many birds have a mechanism called <a href="https://simple.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tendon_locking" rel="nofollow">Tedon Locking</a>, which locks in their feet so that they don’t fall off. I don’t think I’ll find that exceptionally comfortable and safe and indeed there are described cases of these animals falling off.</p> <p>This shows a support for not needing to have beds. However, in the same vein, most animals don’t wear clothes and those seem to be quite helpful against the cold. Tools define the man and the bed could be an impactful one.</p> <p>There’s evidence that our sleep is different and much <a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/evan.21464" rel="nofollow">deeper than our close ancestors</a>. We sleep less and have better intellect. This points to be a</p> <h3>Conclusion</h3> <p>The wider spread of beds</p><!--]-->]]></content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Alpha catan: AI from the ground up</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/alpha_catan"/>
<id>https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/alpha_catan</id>
<published>2024-10-23T00:00:00.000Z</published>
<updated>2024-10-23T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
<content type="html"><![CDATA[<!--[--><h1>Building an AI</h1> <p>For the better part of the last year, I’ve been working on a little project I called <a href="https://github.com/lcmchris/alpha-catan" rel="nofollow"><code>alpha-catan</code></a>. I wanted to work on something just fun and interesting. Nothing related to business or anything that is even (remotely) useful. Just pure unadulterated fun. The project I ended up working on is trying to build and AI that plays Catan.</p> <p>Now, Settlers of Catan is a pretty famous board game which I have personally despised for ages. Apart from the terrible experiences of fights during Catan, I strongly believe there are 2 fundamental flaws of the game.</p> <ol><li><p>Economy acceleration through luck: There is a strong economy acceleration effect. Good rolls give you resources which gives you more settlements… giving you more chances for good rolls. The <code>skill</code> is where to put your settlements. This however creates a situation where in some games you become merely an observer waiting for the winner to slowly play out the game.</p></li> <li><p>Trading: Many will argue the main game is the trading. From my experience, it is merely a tool to abuse new players. There is no reason really to trade as it is a zero-sum game. You would only accept a trade if you would increase your win% and a trade cannot do it for both parties of the trade. The only argument is if coming 2nd vs 3rd matters (which in general party games, it doesn’t).</p></li></ol> <p>These flaws are also why I believe a relatively simple model can beat the majority of players. If the only action that matters is mostly the first one, then it should be relatively simple to solve!
Armed with the <code>Hands on Machine learning book</code> and my hatred of Catan, I started working on building the model and the controller that goes with it.</p> <p>Objective: Beat average player on colonist.io</p> <h2>Building the model</h2> <p>On the outset, I wanted to do most things from scratch meaning I decided to not use a framework or any existing repos. I wanted to learn the basics of ML/RL and I got a lot of inspiration from the <a href="https://www.kaggle.com/code/scaomath/simple-neural-network-for-mnist-numpy-from-scratch" rel="nofollow">toy mnist problem with numpy</a> and <a href="https://karpathy.github.io/2016/05/31/rl/" rel="nofollow">Karpathy’s pong writeup</a>.</p> <p>The model I wanted to build is a basic one. For input game state, predict a suitable action.</p> <p>Inputs</p> <ul><li>Game state <ul><li>Players resources</li> <li>Players dev cards</li> <li>Board state</li></ul></li></ul> <p>Prediction:</p> <ul><li>Action to perform</li></ul> <p>To model multiple actions per turn, we predict until the model sets pass. This assumes that each action is the same regardless of if it is part of a chain of actions or not.</p> <p>Example: Turn</p> <ul><li>Action 1</li> <li>Action 2</li> <li>Action 3</li> <li>until… Pass</li></ul> <p>To start off with and not wanting to scale up training a lot, I focused on a 2-player rendition of the game. It is simpler letting me focus on training to win.</p> <h2>Metrics</h2> <p>The main metric I looked at is <strong>turns to win</strong>. This helps ensure that they get generically better and better. The other are standard ML metrics <strong>avg loss</strong> (indicating how close action vs prediction) and <strong>avg rewards</strong> (the number of rewards for each player).
The expectation is that <strong>turns to win</strong> trends low, <strong>avg loss</strong> trends low and <strong>avg rewards</strong> tampers to a steady level.</p> <h3>Reward allocation and the law of large numbers</h3> <p><strong>Reward allocation</strong> is a tricky business and I struggled in finding a good one. It’s essentially coming up with an intuition and then trying to build for it. For instance, the earliest edition involved only rewarding winners. This is basically running experiments!
The main difficulty comes from which action to reward. In this simple example below:</p> <p>A → B → C → D → E → Win</p> <p>… it’s unclear how much reward to allocate to each of the actions. The best reward is to reward for winning and let the model learn which actions are important. However, the longer the list of actions, the more fuzzy the allocation gets. In theory, based on the law of large numbers, it doesn’t matter (too much) but not having intermediate rewards drastically lower training speed. However, on the flip-side, overengineering the rewards would put too much human intuition to it and make it work via defined rules rather than learned rules.</p> <h4>Rewarding winners</h4> <p>The thought was the as you reward the winner’s actions, it will keep competing until it becomes the best.
Here shows the metrics:</p> <h4>Rewarding winners, Penalizing losers</h4> <p>Other than that, we could also penalize losers. This will speed up</p> <h4>Rewarding Settlements and Cities</h4> <p>Settlements and cities are pretty useful. Let’s reward them</p> <h4>Rewarding points</h4> <p>A limitation of the settlements and cities approach is that it does not reward you if you get dev cards and or longest roads etc.</p> <p>Rewarding points could be a good middle ground.</p> <h4>Training by evolution</h4> <p>An alternative to training on each player winning and losing is to train on the average winner over a batch. Although this could be slower (1/2 of rewards), it should be more accurate on which side is better, giving a better gradient.</p> <h4>Action space rebalancing</h4> <p>One thing that I noticed while training is that it overprioritised non-passing. A simple look at the action space and it’s became clear that because most actions have more than one action, passing is rarely randomly chosen. Rebalancing by a factor of the available actions looks to be a good idea. The idea here is to make passing initially the most possible action and let it slowly fall down.</p> <h2>Building the colonist.io controller</h2> <p>The colonist.io controller was much more difficult and time consuming than I thought. Because of a lack of apis to get the state of the game. The difficulty increases because colonist.io uses a html canvas to display the game. This means it’s not possible to search for elements. What I ended up having to building an image matcher in order to get the state of the game. This includes mapping each of the little settlements and city icons and use cv2 to find where it matches the most. Here is the list of all little images.</p> <p>[]</p> <p>There are essenetially many timeouts added to wait out animations. The images do not always match 100% making it also a bit unreliable.</p> <p>The canvas itself is also not the only piece of the information puzzle. The messages also need to be parsed inorder to provide additional information on whether dev cards are, what was rolled and what resources was gained.</p> <h3>Combining the two</h3> <p>Using the state gathered by the controller, I pass it to our latest and greatest model to battle it out with the colonist.io AI.</p> <p>Here’s a short video of this.</p> <p>Over 100 games… we won…</p><!--]-->]]></content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Waxy breakdown of garlic and experimental design.</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/waxy_breakdown"/>
<id>https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/waxy_breakdown</id>
<published>2024-10-07T00:00:00.000Z</published>
<updated>2024-12-07T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
<content type="html"><![CDATA[<!--[--><p><a href="https://bpp.oregonstate.edu/sites/agscid7/files/bpp/attachments/waxy-breakdown-of-garlic-feb-7-mlp.pdf" rel="nofollow">Waxy breakdown</a> of garlic is a phenomenon where garlic can go translucent and yellow. The pyruvic acid levels of the garlic also reduces, lowering its pugency and has a softer texture.
It’s considered a disease? but
It’s different to black garlic which is fermented.</p> <p>I’ve had it happen a few times to my stash of garlic. I was initially weary about using it as it look’s off, but once I did, I really enjoyed it. It’s taste is much more mellow letting me use it more sparingly. The softer texture also makes it smearable allowing it to be easily added to a marinade or paste.</p> <p>It’s described as a defect by some sources but I didn’t really find any fault in it.</p> <p>What really interests me is that although Garlic is a main seasoning in a chef’s arsenal, there is relatively little research on how and why it develops.</p> <h2>Design of expeirments</h2> <p>I currently work at a bio-tech startup and a statistical approach to analyse variation based on factors is through Design of Experiments (DOE).</p> <h3>What is DOE?</h3> <p>A famous example of DOE is the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lady_tasting_tea" rel="nofollow">lady tasting tea</a> experiment done by Ronald Fischer. In it, Ronald faces a lady who proposes she can tell the difference of if <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=InWGdojtWys" rel="nofollow">milk is poured first or tea is poured first</a>.</p> <p>To test this claim, Ronald devised the null hypothesis that she cannot determine between the two. He then asks what is the minimum about of tests to conduct to be confident enough for.
Im it he decides making 8 teas is good, 4 with milk first and 4 with milk second. Why 8?
All possible combinations of these 8 are 70. Based on pure chance, getting it all right has one possible combination. This sets the experiment with signifcance level of 1/70.</p> <h3>Why DOE?</h3> <p>Experiments are expensive. As a sciencitist you would like to conduct the least amount while preserving reliability and information space that it provides. Leveraging statistics help define how confident you can be and optimise for certain factors to test.</p> <h3>How does DOE work?</h3> <p>One can extend the above to more factors and even analyse <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Confounding" rel="nofollow">confounding factors</a>. The search/test space gets exponentially greater as you will need to test much more combinations.</p> <p>Factors also have levels and their relationships can also be non-linear.</p> <p>Temp
Humidity</p> <p>Implementing DOE in our experiment.</p> <p><a href="https://www.ipt.us.com/produce-inspection-resources/inspectors-blog/defect-identification/garlic-waxy-breakdown" rel="nofollow">https://www.ipt.us.com/produce-inspection-resources/inspectors-blog/defect-identification/garlic-waxy-breakdown</a> Variables:
Heat
Humidity
Time
Sunlight
Closed container?
Salt?
Sugar?
Peeled vs Blubs vs untouched</p> <p>Proxy setup:
I unfortunately do not have precise temperature or humidity guages, nore have thav con trols for them. In their stead I’m using situations that are common in my hosue.</p> <ul><li>China(orange) - Spain(blue)</li> <li>Fridge/Cabinent/Sun</li> <li>Bagged/left out</li> <li>Broken - Bulb</li></ul> <p><strong>Cabinent</strong> China - Cabinent - Out - Bulb
China - Cabinent - Bagged - Broken
China - Cabinent - Bagged - Bulb</p> <p>Spain - Cabinent - Bagged - Broken
Spain - Cabinent - Out - Broken
Spain - Cabinent - Out - Bulb</p> <p><strong>Sun</strong> China - Sun - Out - Bulb
China - Sun - Bagged - Broken
China - Sun - Out - Broken</p> <p>Spain - Sun - Out - Bulb
Spain - Sun - Bagged - Broken
Spain - Sun - Out - Broken</p> <p><strong>Fridge</strong> China - Fridge - Out - Bulb
China - Fridge - Bagged - Broken
China - Fridge - Out - Broken</p> <p>Spain - Fridge - Bagged - Bulb
Spain - Fridge - Bagged - Broken</p> <h2>As of 21-11-2024</h2> <p><strong>Cabinent</strong> China - Cabinent - Out - Bulb
China - Cabinent - Bagged - Broken
China - Cabinent - Bagged - Bulb</p> <p>Spain - Cabinent - Bagged - Broken - 1/10
Spain - Cabinent - Out - Broken
Spain - Cabinent - Out - Bulb</p> <p><strong>Sun</strong> China - Sun - Out - Bulb
China - Sun - Bagged - Broken
China - Sun - Out - Broken</p> <p>Spain - Sun - Out - Bulb
Spain - Sun - Bagged - Broken
Spain - Sun - Out - Broken</p> <p><strong>Fridge</strong> China - Fridge - Out - Bulb
China - Fridge - Bagged - Broken
China - Fridge - Out - Broken</p> <p>Spain - Fridge - Bagged - Bulb
Spain - Fridge - Bagged - Broken</p> <h2>As of 03-12-2024</h2> <p>no change</p> <h2>As of 06-12-2024</h2> <p>no change</p> <h1>Final 06-01-2024</h1> <p><strong>Cabinent</strong> China - Cabinent - Out - Bulb - 9 no change
China - Cabinent - Bagged - Broken -6 no chang
China - Cabinent - Bagged - Bulb - 1 sprouted, 1 rotten, 11 no change</p> <p>Spain - Cabinent - Bagged - Broken - 1 success! 10 no change.
Spain - Cabinent - Out - Broken - 9 no change
Spain - Cabinent - Out - Bulb - 7 no change, 1 sprouted</p> <p><strong>Sun</strong> China - Sun - Out - Bulb - 1 sprouted, 10 no change
China - Sun - Bagged - Broken - 11 no change
China - Sun - Out - Broken - 9 no change</p> <p>Spain - Sun - Out - Bulb - 1 sprouted, 9 no change
Spain - Sun - Bagged - Broken - 2 weird ones with babies, 9 no change
Spain - Sun - Out - Broken -2 sprouted, 8 no change</p> <p><strong>Fridge</strong> China - Fridge - Out - Bulb - 9 sprouted, 3 no change
China - Fridge - Bagged - Broken - 8 sprouted, 1 no change
China - Fridge - Out - Broken - 11 no change</p> <p>Spain - Fridge - Bagged - Bulb - fully rotten
Spain - Fridge - Bagged - Broken - 7 sprouted, 2 rotten</p> <h2>Summary</h2> <p>There was literally only one garlic that changed to the desired waxy form so it’s hard to have any conclusions. I have done this in the past and got much higher success rate so it could really be determined by the batch of garlic.</p><!--]-->]]></content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>My computer setup</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/my_computer_setup"/>
<id>https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/my_computer_setup</id>
<published>2024-06-07T00:00:00.000Z</published>
<updated>2024-06-07T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
<content type="html"><![CDATA[<!--[--><p>To put things into context, my primary purposes for a computer is to program, watch videos and play video games. That’s pretty much it and accounts for all I need a computer from.</p> <p>I prefer a setup with minimal fuss and can be flexible enough to adapt to either new technologies and games.</p> <p>In this post I aim to cover a few of the choices I’ve made and why I’ve made them.</p> <h2>My hardware</h2> <p>Currently in my disposable are:</p> <ul><li>PC <a href="https://uk.pcpartpicker.com/list/6pc9MV" rel="nofollow">specs</a></li> <li>Laptop <a href="https://www.asus.com/laptops/for-home/vivobook/vivobook-s14-s410/techspec/" rel="nofollow">specs</a></li> <li>Work Laptop</li></ul> <h3>OS</h3> <p>I’ve been a long time user of Windows but am always aware of possible benefits of switching to Linux/Mac Os. As I don’t have money to kill, Mac was always out of the question. There are also potential drawbacks mainly because there will be games that are only compatible with Windows.</p> <p>For linux, there is much better support for development tools. Tools like pyenv, bash, docker, just work natively. Even just base path manipulation is much easier without <a href="https://www.fileside.app/blog/2023-03-17_windows-file-paths/" rel="nofollow">weird windows paths</a>.</p> <p>There is the possibility to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Multi-booting" rel="nofollow">dual boot</a> but that seems like pain to manage.</p> <p>To mitigate it, WSL looks to be the best of both worlds. It’s support looks to be a priority for microsoft and there’s been consistent releases and good guides on getting setup.</p> <p>I’ve used WSL now on my home PC and work laptop.</p> <p>Gotchas. WSL can be slow, uses loads of memory and sometimes freezes.</p> <p>For my personal laptop, I’m somewhat limited by the hardware. It’s been use for 6 years now and the battery is dropping off. Everything performs slow on that laptop making it hardly productive. I only use it when I go to a cafe to write or program (so no games). To breath some new life into it, I decided to install linux mint onto it. It’s been much more responsive and the battery life seems to be better (probably due to the wipe not the os).</p> <p>There are many tools in</p> <ul><li><p>OS</p> <ul><li>WSL</li> <li>Linux Mint!</li></ul></li> <li><p>Code Editor</p> <ul><li>VSCode + extensions</li></ul></li> <li><p>Env Management</p> <ul><li>Pyenv</li> <li>Nvm</li> <li>Poetry</li> <li>Pnpm</li></ul></li></ul> <h1>IDE</h1> <p>I started out programming with Eclipse on the Oxygen release. I used the PyDev extension and was building a little Selenium application to automate some UI testing. I also tried out Atom to help write some python automation scripts. Both tools felt like they weren’t providing me with a lot. They had poor ui and is limited to someone who just want’s to build stuff.</p> <p>I started using VScode and its just much more beginner friendly, more multi-language friendly and has tons of community support. It now also works well with WSL (both being microsoft).</p> <p>Very recently, I’ve been inspired to learn Vim and started to use th VScodeVim extension. It’s worked quite well so far and it is always nice to learn a new skill.</p> <h2>Environment managers</h2> <p>I primarily program in Python (AI) or Javascript (Apps).</p> <p>For python, one of the main issues when trying to access multiple different repos is the python version compatability. Later versions of python have features the old versions do not. Managing python versions is super annoying and installing all of them and switching between them is not easy out of the box. A tool I’ve been using is Pyenv which allows you to switch python versions very easily.</p> <p>For node, I use the equivalently helpful nvm tool.</p> <h2>Package managers</h2> <p>The pacakge manager for python I use is Poetry. It provides version locking and venv handling. It’s a pretty tried and tested tool. PDM is the new comer on the block but I have not tried it yet.</p> <p>For node, I use pnpm (a drop in for npm).
There’s bun and yarn too to try but again I haven’t done the work.</p><!--]-->]]></content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Is physical writing still important in our generation?</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/is_writing_important"/>
<id>https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/is_writing_important</id>
<published>2024-01-01T00:00:00.000Z</published>
<updated>2024-01-01T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
<content type="html"><![CDATA[<!--[--><h1>Context</h1> <p>I was born and raised in Hong Kong for over 15 years, and would consider myself
a native Cantonese speaker. However, if you asked me to physically write Chinese
characters in order to save a cute little puppy🐶… it would unfortunately not
make it.</p> <p>Why is that? Why can read, speak and listen to Chinese perfectly fine but have
such a low grasp on writing. I’ve read the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Remembrance_of_Earth%27s_Past" rel="nofollow">Remembrance of Earth’s Past Trilogy</a> and other books with no clear issues. So <strong>why is the physical act of writing
impossible for me?</strong> This activity seems to require a different collection of
memory and a different way of learning.</p> <p>A further argument is that since I can function in Chinese, maybe the physical
act of writing is a remnant of the past.</p> <h1>What is going on when I try to write Chinese characters?</h1> <p>If I can express ideas verbally, shouldn’t I be able to write them as well? This
is what I do in English. This is what I do in English. You can tell in my tone
here that I approach writing in a casual, speaking-like manner. However, when I
take pen to paper in Chinese, my mind goes totally blank and I can’t even piece
together a proper sentence.</p> <p>An <strong>incorrect</strong> analogy is forgetting how to spell a word in English. In
English, by pronouncing the word I can probably fudge it and make it 90% there.
In Chinese, it’s more like trying to do a life-like painting of a person you
know. It’s clear as day what this person looks like but when you start, you
realise all the detail is not there. I often can start by trying to imagine
reading the character in a book and attempting to replicate it. For most
characters that I don’t recall, my success rate would be less than 20%.</p> <p>The size of the gap between my reading versus my writing.</p> <p>An obvious reason is that Chinese is a logogram writing system. This is where
writing is based on logos/symbols/characters and not based phonetically. This
means knowing how to say a word has almost no bearing on how to write it. I say
almost as there are usually 部首 that do guide pronunciation.</p> <h1>Is Typing the same as writing?</h1> <p>I type using Pinyin. Pinyin is the phonetic conversion of a character
constructed using the alphabet. Pinyin sprouted around the 50s and is taught
around the world. There are other input methods using an array of different
philosophies like the order of strokes.</p> <blockquote><p>Using Pinyin’s 2 has core strengths. One, I can sound the word out. Two, I can
use the keyboard assistance to read the potential options.</p></blockquote> <p><strong>To me, writing is a way to communicate ideas to readers.</strong></p> <p>Whether I write those words or type those words doesn’t seem too critical. I
wouldn’t write this article on paper first and then re-type it out, and the the
reader also wouldn’t know/care.</p> <p>If the goal is to convey information to many people, typing might even be a more
important skill of the language to learn. To further push this established
premise, I tried learning Japanese for around 3 months. My teacher never once
brought up teaching me how to write Kanji. It seemed to be a given that I would
learn how to type instead.</p> <h1>Conclusion</h1> <p>My final conclusion is that learning to physically write is no longer an
important facet of languages. The design of prose and command of vocabulary are
vital to good writing.</p><!--]-->]]></content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Ongoing musings</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/ongoing_musings"/>
<id>https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/ongoing_musings</id>
<published>2024-01-01T00:00:00.000Z</published>
<updated>2024-12-01T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
<content type="html"><![CDATA[<!--[--><h1>Random thoughts</h1> <h3>Is writing any language important in our generation?✅</h3> <ul><li>Fluency of language</li> <li>Reading vs writing vs listening vs speaking</li> <li>Writing versus typing</li> <li>Can there be a universal language?</li></ul> <h3>~~ How good is Feng shui 風水?~~</h3> <ul><li><del>Is Feng shui based on good UX?</del></li> <li><del>Who still uses feng shui?</del></li></ul> <h3>When did people start sleeping on their backs?✅</h3> <ul><li>Invention of the pillow?</li></ul> <h3>Why is most programming languages english?</h3> <ul><li>Information density of languages</li> <li>History of programming</li> <li>Exciting languages that uses different languages</li></ul> <h3>Factfulness now?</h3> <ul><li>Factfulness was an interesting book</li> <li>How true has it been in the last ten years?</li> <li>Will it stay try?</li></ul> <h3>Experiment on waxy breakdown of garlic</h3> <ul><li>Waxy breakdown of Garlic</li> <li>Other types of garlic breakdown</li> <li>Sets of experiments</li> <li>Reproducibility?</li> <li>Strains? - Putting my bio labskills to the test</li></ul> <h3>My coding setup</h3> <ul><li>OS <ul><li>WSL!</li> <li>Linux Mint!</li></ul></li> <li>Code Editor <ul><li>VSCode + extensions</li></ul></li> <li>Python Env Management <ul><li>Pyenv</li> <li>Poetry</li></ul></li> <li>Bash setup</li></ul> <h3>Baking AI / Receipes AI</h3> <p>An AI taht generates new recipes</p> <h3>UK health labels</h3> <p>What does the health labels mean, and why some has colours.</p> <h3>The stagnation of Travelling</h3> <ul><li>Travelling when young</li> <li>Travelling when older</li> <li>Travelling or vactioning</li></ul> <h3>How to ideate?</h3> <ul><li>Ideas that are fun</li> <li>Ideas that make money</li></ul> <h3>Anonymity or Named?</h3> <ul><li>Github</li> <li>Blog</li> <li>Skin in the game</li></ul> <h3>Building a new typeface</h3> <ul><li>How to create a typeface?</li> <li>Introducing my own typeface</li></ul> <h3>Information hierarchy</h3> <ul><li>Spectrum of watching, listening, reading, speaking and writing.</li> <li>Getting information to creating information</li></ul> <h1>Fiction</h1> <p>City of clouds</p> <ul><li>Cloud Emperor</li> <li>Molten core with a dense cloud</li> <li>Cloud archeticture</li> <li>Flora of vines and flowers</li></ul> <p>Ride to somwhere ✅</p> <h2>Types of time spent</h2> <ul><li>Learning</li> <li>Performing</li> <li>Enjoying</li></ul><!--]-->]]></content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Pickpockets operate at this station.</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/pickpockets_operate_at_this_station"/>
<id>https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/pickpockets_operate_at_this_station</id>
<published>2024-01-01T00:00:00.000Z</published>
<updated>2024-01-01T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
<content type="html"><![CDATA[<!--[--><p>This phrase is played across London tube stations. The nonchalant and robotic tone of the broadcast sounds as though the pickpocketers simply work at the station. In line with the “See it, say it and sort it” and “No Staring” posters, it brings a looming inevitability that hooliganism is always by our side.</p> <p>How do these safety reminders give Londoners and visitors a sense of security? If nothing else, it adds to the pervasiveness of lawlessness and keenly suggests that the system cannot protect you. Fend for yourselves lest you get robbed. This distasteful tone underlines London’s coldness and inhumanness. As a community, we seem to need an active message that these things are wrong and to help others.</p> <p>Right and wrong is lost and the common respect for a society is gone. The rubbish found inside the tube and station is also absolutely appalling. Random bottles and food packaging are just lying on any possible flat surface, including the floor, seats and handrails. Chewing gum everywhere. Instead of convincing good citizens to confront, we need to build a strong guilt system against petty crimes and behaviours.</p><!--]-->]]></content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Ride to somewhere</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/ride_to_somewhere"/>
<id>https://lcmchris.github.io/posts/ride_to_somewhere</id>
<published>2024-01-01T00:00:00.000Z</published>
<updated>2024-01-01T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
<content type="html"><![CDATA[<!--[--><h1>Ride to somewhere</h1> <p>I open my eyes. I’m on a bus. It’s packed and stuffy. The people around me speak a language I do not understand. The window on my left shows a scenery of shrubs and more shrubs. My right shows a barren rocky landscape.</p> <p>A gentleman is sitting next to me. His cane is lodged between his legs, and he wears a mismatched tweed suit and beige chino pants. I asked him where we were and where we were heading but got nothing more than a shrug. There is no information about where the bus is going.</p> <p>I try to relax. The bus stops every half a minute with many people getting on and off. A mom with a stroller gets on and off at the same station. This must be the wrong bus for her. The twists and turns of the journey make me want to vomit. I check my backpack only to find a blank notebook, without a pen.</p> <p>I close my eyes and drift into an uneasy sleep. As I wake up, I realise I’m still on the bus, heading somewhere.</p><!--]-->]]></content>
</entry>
</feed>
